<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The blind obedience of an humble penitent the best cure for scruples</title>
            <author>Jenks, Sylvester, 1656?-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 116 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J629</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26825</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09551072</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09551072</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43611</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46795)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43611)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1334:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The blind obedience of an humble penitent the best cure for scruples</title>
                  <author>Jenks, Sylvester, 1656?-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 216 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Sylvester Jenks--Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scruples.</term>
               <term>Christian ethics.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43611:1"/>
            <p>THE BLIND OBEDIENCE OF AN HUMBLE PENITENT. THE Beſt Cure for Scruples.</p>
            <p>AN. DOM. M.DC.XCVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:43611:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <p>D. <hi>A.</hi> 19. <hi>A.</hi> 1698.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. H.</hi> L. C.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:43611:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Crupuloſity is a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of the Mind, which many people have more or leſs of; although few believe it, &amp; fewer are willing to own it. The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part, &amp; the wiſeſt, are commonly ashamed of it. But yet there are ſome (the few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the better) who think it a fine thing to be longer than ordinary, in conſulting, in preparing, &amp; confeſſing. The more they out-do their neighbours in theſe matters, &amp; the more they are taken notice of for being ſingular,
<pb facs="tcp:43611:3"/>ſo much more they admire themſelves for being skillfull, carefull, &amp; exact. They ſeem to affect theſe tedious &amp; tormenting Scrupuloſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as if they thought them to be the Modish Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Saints: And, if one may judge by appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they are like a certain Lady, who having entertain'd the company with a long hiſtory of her Vapours, could not endure to hear a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, inferiour to her ſelf, begin to complain of the ſame indiſpoſition. <hi>Marry come up,</hi> ſays her Ladyship, <hi>we shall have every body, one of theſe days, take upon them to be troubled with Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours,
<pb facs="tcp:43611:3"/>if ſuch as you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis hard to determine which is greater, the Folly or the Miſchief of Scrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſity. Take it one way, there is no ſubject more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious: take it the other, there is nothing more ridiculous. My chief deſign is to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Miſchief of it, without ſparing the Folly, when it happens to lie in my way. And truly, when peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are ſo fond of their Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, I am apt to think, it is not amiſs to let them ſee how ſilly the humour is. There is always a ſecret Pride lies lurking in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, when they are ſo ſtiff
<pb facs="tcp:43611:4"/>in their opinion; and a little ſenſe of shame is in ſome meaſure a remedy for it. If one always treat theſe follies with reſpect &amp; gravity, it will onely ſerve to confirm them in a vain belief, that their miſtakes are wiſe ones: And this <hi>being wiſe in their own conceits</hi> is the chief part of their Diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>In fine, well or ill, I have now done Scribling: And, upon ſecond thoughts, am in ſome admiration how I ever prevail'd with my ſelf, to begin. But, being once enter'd, and having already publish'd
<note n="*" place="bottom">A Contrite &amp; Humble Heart: Three Sermons upon the Sacrament: A Letter concerning the Council of Trent: &amp;c.</note> ſome ſmall Pieces,
<pb facs="tcp:43611:4"/>I was not willing to leave off, till I had made a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of this little Treatiſe to my Friends; to whom if it prove acceptable &amp; uſefull, I shall not think my labour loſt: And, for the reſt, the care is taken.</p>
            <p>Mean time I keep my name to my ſelf: And my reaſon is, becauſe I love a quiet life. I ever lookt upon it as the greateſt bleſſing which a bad World can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford: and am perſwaded that being Private is the eaſieſt &amp; ſecureſt way of being Quiet. Beſides, I ſee no good there is in being talkt of; either well, or ill: The one
<pb facs="tcp:43611:5"/>is good for nothing but to make a man Vain; the other is as apt to make him Vext; and All to no purpoſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page.</hi> 40. <hi>line.</hi> 23. <hi>dele</hi> we. <hi>page.</hi> 84. <hi>line.</hi> 20. <hi>dele</hi> the, <hi>page.</hi> 90. <hi>line.</hi> 21. <hi>read</hi> get. <hi>page</hi> 92. <hi>line</hi> 1. <hi>read</hi> harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. <hi>page.</hi> 135. <hi>line.</hi> 15. <hi>read</hi> they. <hi>page.</hi> 167. <hi>line.</hi> 1. dele <hi>they.</hi> Theſe, &amp; ſuch other over-ſights of the Preſs, the Reader (I hope) will eaſily pardon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:43611:5"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> THe Character of Blind Obedience, &amp; of Scrupuloſity which is humble and ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive. <hi>pag. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The true Cauſes of proud &amp; willfull Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puloſity. <hi>7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The extravagant Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Scrupuloſity, when it is proud &amp; willfull. <hi>10</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>§. 1.</hi> The extravagancy of their Curioſity. <hi>12</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>§. 2.</hi> The extravagancy of their Examens. <hi>20</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>§. 3.</hi> The extravagancy of their Fears. <hi>25</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> The pernicious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of the ſame Scrupuloſity. <hi>28</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:43611:6"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>§. 1.</hi> The difference bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wixt Servile Fear, &amp; Loving Confidence. <hi>31</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>§. 2.</hi> The miſchief of long Examens. <hi>36</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>§. 3.</hi> Blind Obedience the beſt Remedy. <hi>44</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Nothing more unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable than a boundleſs Liberty of reaſoning. <hi>47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The difference bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wixt a Philoſopher &amp; a Chriſtian, concerning the Submiſſion of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Reaſon. <hi>56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The different Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of a Proud &amp; an Humble Penitent, concerning Blind Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. <hi>60</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> A Scripture-Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection anſwer'd. <hi>69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Pretences of Reaſon anſwer'd. <hi>75</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:43611:6"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Pretences of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence conſider'd. <hi>96</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>§. 1.</hi> The two ſorts of Practical Certainty ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd. <hi>101</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>§. 2.</hi> When we rely upon our Confeſſor's Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, our Certainty is Abſolute. <hi>103</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>§. 3.</hi> When we depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Probability of our own Reaſon, our Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty is onely Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional. <hi>118</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>§. 4.</hi> Objections of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Conſcience anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer'd. <hi>138</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> The Security of Blind Obedience pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Scripture. <hi>153</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Maxims of S. <hi>BERNARD</hi> concerning Blind Obedience. <hi>169</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:43611:7"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>MAX. I.</hi> We ought to look upon our Confeſſor as a Vicegerent of God, without conſidering his faults. <hi>171</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>MAX. II.</hi> We ought to look upon him as our Judge, without examining his reaſons. <hi>184</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <head>APPROBATION.</head>
            <p>I Have read this learned Treatiſe, concerning <hi>Blind Obedience,</hi> which I judge very uſefull; &amp; obſerved no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it, but ſolid &amp; orthodox. <hi>Dat. Lovanij.</hi> 17. <hi>Aprilis.</hi> 1698.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>FRANCIS MARTIN. <hi>Doctor &amp; Royal Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of Divinity in the Univerſity of Lovain.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43611:7"/>
            <head>THE BLIND <hi>OBEDIENCE</hi> OF AN HUMBLE <hi>PENITENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Character of Blind Obedience, and of Scrupuloſity which is humble &amp; ſubmiſſive.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Lind Obedience is an ill name which the World has given to one of the beſt things in it. I do not call it ſo, becauſe I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43611:8"/>think it is ſo; but becauſe the cuſtom of ſpeaking will have it ſo, and many people will not underſtand me if I uſe another term for it. However I shall endeavour to do it ſo much juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, as to shew plainly in a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar example, that ſo good a thing does not deſerve ſo bad a name.</p>
               <p>Let us ſuppoſe two Travellers in the ſame way to the ſame home, &amp; that their lives &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes depend upon their coming timely thither. The one goes ſlowly on, &amp; oftentimes ſtands ſtill to ſatisfie his curioſity, either in looking back to take a proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the Country which he leaves behind him, or elſe in ſtudying whether the foot-way on the right hand or the left be better than the way he's in: Whileſt he is thus amuſed with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43611:8"/>idle fancies, time runs on, the day is ſpent, he is benighted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is aware, &amp; begins to repent when 'tis too late. His fellow-traveller conſiders that all theſe vain amuſements are nothing to his purpoſe, he is full of concern for the great affair he has in hand, &amp; therefore he marches diligently on, minds carefully the way before him, &amp; never ſtops to look behind, or gaze about him. Will any body ſay, this man is blind, becauſe he does not ſee backward? or becauſe he does not ſtare about him, on the one ſide, or the other? All his buſineſs is to go forward, he ſees the way before him as well as any man living, he ſees all that he has need to ſee, and therefore, whoſoever ſays this man is blind, muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me if I cannot believe it.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:43611:9"/>
               <p>The Caſe of theſe two Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers is dayly verified in ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous perſons, of which there are two ſorts: the one proud &amp; willfull, the other humble &amp; ſubmiſſive. Thoſe rely upon themſelves, &amp; theſe upon their Guide. Thoſe always are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turb'd with idle doubts &amp; fears which are not worth a ſerious thought: Theſe never trouble their heads with any thing but their chief buſineſs, which is to march diligently on, for fear of coming late; they never ſtop to look backward, for fear of having dropt ſomething behind them; they never ſtand ſtill to obſerve the different paths on either ſide of the road; they carefully ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſure direction of their Guide, and, without diſputing the matter with him, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to follow whereſoêre he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43611:9"/>leads. This is the true character of the Obedience I ſpeak of: It is always ready to march at firſt word of command; it never pauſes to gaze behind it, or on either ſide; it clearly ſees the way which it is bid to take, &amp; never perplexes it ſelf with any doubts about it, becauſe it is ſelf-evident there can be no other way for true Obedience. What a ſpitefull thing it is, to ſay, that this Obedience is <hi>blind,</hi> when it <hi>ſees</hi> its way ſo <hi>clearly,</hi> &amp; is ſo <hi>certain</hi> of it!</p>
               <p>This humble &amp; ſubmiſſive Scrupuloſity is rather to be envied, than be pitied. To theſe there is no need of preaching Blind Obedience. They are very well acquainted with it: 'tis their dayly prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, &amp; perpetual comfort: 'tis by this they overcome their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43611:10"/>doubts &amp; fears; and though they are not quite ſo eaſy as they would be, yet they are conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; reſign'd. Their Scrupulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, though ſometimes pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, is always advantagious to them: the experience of their weakneſs humbles them, &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifies them in the practice of Obedience, it not onely puts them in the way to Heaven; but it helps to keep them in it; and therefore I have no more to ſay to them at preſent, but onely to wish them a good journey. The proud &amp; willfull Sinners are the perſons, I have now to deal with: Thoſe Sinners who are not contented to be Saints <hi>according to God's heart,</hi> but <hi>muſt</hi> &amp; <hi>will</hi> be <hi>Saints</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their <hi>own.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:43611:10"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The true Cauſes of proud &amp; willfull Scrupuloſity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OUr Doctors &amp; Divines, who treat of Scruples, obſerve ſeveral cauſes of them: 1. Melancholy, which is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times cured by phyſick: 2. Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of the Devil, againſt whom the beſt defence is prayer: 3. Converſation of Scrupulous perſons, whoſe needleſs diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of their inward troubles, ought to be shunn'd as infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious: 4. Reading of caſuiſtical books, which are to be avoided as remedies unfit for the diſeaſe: 5. Exceſs of ſervile fear, which dayly diminishes as the Love of God encreaſes. Theſe are the Cauſes which they commonly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43611:11"/>take notice of; but they are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to my preſent purpoſe: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a complication of them all together, may conſiſt with being humble &amp; ſubmiſſive.</p>
               <p>The true &amp; proper Cauſes of our being proud &amp; willfull in our Scruples, are the Eſteem of our Judgment, &amp; the Love of our Liberty, which we derive originally from the Sin of our firſt Parents. We are curious of <hi>knowing good &amp; evil:</hi> we are am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious of <hi>being like the Higheſt:</hi> we are deſirous of being abſolute and independent in all our thoughts &amp; actions: we would willingly be uncontrollable in both: we would fain do what we think, &amp; think what we pleaſe: in a word, we would gladly chuſe our own way, and be our own Judges whether we have choſen right or wrong.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:43611:11"/>
               <p>Tis obvious to every body's natural reaſon, that Scrupulous perſons would never be proud, if they had not an eſteem of their judgment; neither would they be willfull in their Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, if they did not love the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of their humour. They eſteem their judgment, &amp; are therefore ſo proud, they cannot endure to ſubmit it: they love their humour, &amp; therefore are ſo willfull, they cannot abide to croſs it. To abate this love, &amp; to correct this vain eſteem, I know nothing more proper than to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the folly &amp; the mifcheif which attend them: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore shall endeavour in the two following chapters to shew the extravagant effects, &amp; the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious conſequences of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:43611:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The extravagant Effects of Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puloſity when it is proud &amp; willfull.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TIs no wonder that humane Reaſon is extravagant, when Scrupuloſity on the one ſide, &amp; obſtinacy on the other, conſpire together to confound the notions of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The one frights it out of the way; the other hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it from coming in again: The one warps it; the other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes it ſtand bent: And how is't poſſible for any body to ſquare their actions by ſuch a crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Rule. All that I wonder at, is this; that when people find, &amp; feel by ſad experience, the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; extravagancy of their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſuch a Rule, they are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43611:12"/>yet ſo proud &amp; willfull as not to make uſe of a better, which God himſelf has recommended to them.</p>
               <p>There are ſuch a vaſt variety of follies &amp; exceſſes which their pride &amp; willfullneſs betray them to, that I should never make an end, if I pretended to take notice of them all: &amp; therefore, to bring my matters into as little compaſs as may be, &amp; to make them as plain &amp; ſelf-evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as I can, I shall reduce them to three general heads, by conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the principal duties of Temperance, &amp; by comparing that of the Body with the other of the Mind, which has moſt need of it, &amp; ſuffers moſt for want of it.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:43611:13"/>
                  <head>SECT. I. <hi>The extravagancy of their Curioſity.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe firſt &amp; leaſt degree of Temperance obliges us to abſtain from all thoſe things, which in the common opinion of the world are poyſon to us, &amp; will certainly deſtroy us. A man muſt needs be very intemperate indeed, who longs for a belly-full of Arſenick, as much as a child does for a lump of ſugar. Would you not think a man ſtrangely willfull, who will not believe 'tis poyſon, till he has tried it? Such is the folly of many ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous penitents, who long to know ſome ſecret truths, which if they knew for certain, the very cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty would be enough to ruine
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43611:13"/>them. They fright themſelves al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt out of their wits with thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, that their Confeſſions ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver are exact, that they never love God above all things, that they never do ſufficient pennance for their ſins, that they are not in the ſtate of Grace, &amp; that they are not in the number of God's Elect. How happy should they be, in caſe they did but know aſſuredly the truth of theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant matters! If they knew onely theſe two things, 1. that they are at preſent in God's favour, 2. that they always shall be ſo, How cheerfully &amp; unconcerndly would they then march forward in the way to Heaven!</p>
                  <p>I confeſs, they have all the reaſon in the world to wish theſe things were true: Their Eternal happineſs or miſery depend en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43611:14"/>upon the truth of them: But, ſince they may be true, without their knowledg, 'tis evidently unneceſſary to know it, &amp; unreaſonable to be ſo eager for the aſſurance of it. Alas! all this is nothing but the weakneſs &amp; faint-heartedneſs of an infirm &amp; cowardly Spirit, which makes them over-cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous of their ſecurity: a Security which would eternally undo them, if they had it. They are terribly afraid: this Fear makes them very uneaſy: &amp; this Unea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs creates an earneſt deſire of an imaginary Certainty, which may exempt them from all fear, &amp; make them be at eaſe. In this proceeding there is great appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Humour, but not one jot of Reaſon: &amp; becauſe they are ſuch great pretenders to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I shall take the pains to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43611:14"/>prove that nothing can be more unreaſonable.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. Tis impoſſible for any body to deſire ſincerely the Salvation of their Soul, without deſiring at the ſame time to comply with all thoſe duties, which are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to ſave it. One of theſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties is Fear: we are commanded to
<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.12.</note> 
                     <hi>work our Salvation with Fear &amp; Trembling:</hi> How then can they pretend to go to <hi>work</hi> without it?</p>
                  <p n="2">II. Tis certainly a foolish thing to avoid one miſchief, by incurring another equal to it. A wiſe man, if he were obliged to paſs twixt fire &amp; water, would be ſure to mind the middle-way: he would neither burn himſelf for fear of drowning, nor drown himſelf for fear of burning. This is the preſent caſe. The way to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43611:15"/>Heaven is the middle-way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Preſumption &amp; Deſpair: two dreadfull precipices which deſcend as low as Hell. To ſave us from falling on either ſide, the way is fenc'd with Hope &amp; Fear: Hope, that we may not deſpair, Fear, that we may not preſume. The blood of our veins, and breath of our noſtrils, are not more requiſite for the life of our bodies, than Hope &amp; Fear are neceſſary for the ſaving of our Souls: How then can they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that 'tis reaſonable, to deſire to be exempt from either?</p>
                  <p n="3">III. The onely true Security, which can be expected in this world, is that which is grounded upon Fear. Tis Fear that makes us humble &amp; diligent. By making us humble, it prepares us for the grace of God;
<note n="(b)" place="bottom">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.5.</note> 
                     <hi>He gives</hi> his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43611:15"/>
                     <hi>grace to the humble:</hi> and by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king us diligent in complying with his grace, it helps us to ſecure our Salvation;
<note n="(c)" place="bottom">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Uſe diligence,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>to make your calling &amp; election ſure.</hi> Beſides, 'tis Fear that makes us
<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 26.41.</note> 
                     <hi>watch &amp; pray, that we enter not into temptation.</hi> By <hi>watching</hi> we put our ſelves upon a cloſe guard, and by <hi>praying</hi> we obtain the aſſiſtance of Heaven againſt all our enemies on earth. When
<note n="(e)" place="bottom">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</note> 
                     <hi>our Enemy the Devil goes about like a roaring Lion, ſeeking to devour us,</hi> an unconcernd aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is apt to lull us aſleep: There's nothing like Fear, to make us watchfull.
<note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.1.</note> 
                     <hi>O God incline unto my aid; O Lord, make haſt to help me.</hi> A man, who is afraid, will ſay this prayer
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43611:16"/>heartily: but he, who thinks himſelf in ſafety, will either ſay it very tepidly, or not at all. To conclude in a few words; <hi>Watching</hi> &amp; <hi>Praying</hi> are our beſt <hi>Security: Fear</hi> is the beſt thing in the world, to make us <hi>watch</hi> &amp; <hi>pray:</hi> And therefore, they who are ſo fond of being <hi>Secure,</hi> How can they think of wishing to be <hi>free from Fear?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">IV. The <hi>Fanaticks</hi> pretend to the very ſame aſſurance, which our Scrupulous people are ſo fond of: and Experience plainly teaches, that it onely ſerves to make them proud and negligent. When once they are deluded with a ſtrong perſwaſion that they are God's Favourites, They take no further care: <hi>The Lambs of the Lord may play what tricks they pleaſe.</hi> If this be the effect of unconcernd Security; if it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43611:16"/>poyſon &amp; ruine the Soul; what reaſon can any body have to wish for it?</p>
                  <p n="5">V. As long as the Devil is not dead, and as long as this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full flesh of ours is living in a wicked world; ſo long it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for us to be free from three implacable enemies, the World, the Flesh, &amp; the Devil. Heaven is the onely place of Peace, ſuch as excludes all war, all danger, &amp; all fear:
<note n="(g)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Iob.</hi> 7.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Upon Earth our life is a</hi> continual <hi>Warfare:</hi> &amp; every body knows very well, there can be no <hi>War</hi> without danger, nor <hi>Danger</hi> without juſt reaſon to <hi>fear.</hi> A true Security of being Happy, without any fear of being other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, is undoubtedly a very lovely thing; and Heaven it ſelf is lovely, for the very ſake of it. I
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43611:17"/>do not wonder that good people are in love with it: and that they long to be in Heaven, to enjoy it. But to wish to have it, where we know it is not to be had, is an extravagancy which I never can ſufficiently admire.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II. <hi>The extravagancy of their Examens.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe ſecond degree of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance obliges us, not onely to abſtain from poyſon, but alſo from all exceſs in ſuch meats and drinks as are good &amp; neceſſary for us: and the reaſon is clear; becauſe although they are good, if moderately taken, yet every great exceſs is hurtfull, &amp; next door to poyſon. Let a man be never ſo temperate in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43611:17"/>the choice of his diet: though he be never ſo cautious in conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Phyſician concerning the <hi>quality</hi> of it; yet, if he exceed in the <hi>quantity,</hi> if he eat all day &amp; drink all night, he is certainly guilty of a very notorious intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance.</p>
                  <p>This is the caſe of thoſe Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous Penitents, who are too proud to ſubmit their judgment, &amp; too willfull to croſs their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour. To examine their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, is a very good thing, &amp; neceſſary for the health of their Soul: but yet there's moderation in all things; and 'tis an unpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable extravagancy to ſpend the greateſt part of day &amp; night, in ſpelling upon ſins and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, &amp; putting them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If it were onely ſo much precious time ſo idely ſpent, they would be more excuſable:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43611:18"/>but to employ their time ſo bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily, not onely to do themſelves no good, but even to do them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a great deal of harm, is a folly which I take to be match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs. They torment themſelves continually: they neglect all other duties, they bring a publick ſcandal upon the very character of devotion: and all this to no purpoſe, but onely to try to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the fears of a cowardly Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which has no reaſon in the world to be ſo fearfull, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it wants a little courage to be quiet.</p>
                  <p>I muſt needs own, that when people are ready to ſink under the weight of their uneaſineſs, 'tis natural to ſeek for comfort; but however 'tis not rational to ſeek it where Experience proves it is not to be found. They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43611:18"/>eaſily ſubmit their judgment to their Confeſſor; &amp; therefore in all their doubts they labour to ſuppreſs their fears, by ſatisfying their own Reaſon about them: But the more they range in the Wood, the more they confound &amp; loſe themſelves. They can neither endure the thought of danger, nor the ſenſe of fear; &amp; therefore, though they really believe it is to little purpoſe, yet they ſtill are tempted to go on, &amp; eaſily yield to the temptation. If experience did not teach them that they try in vain, they might have ſome plea their practiſe but to examine barely for examen ſake, is a groundleſs fancy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt colour of reaſon; &amp; looks (if I may borrow the wit of a pleaſant modern Poet)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43611:19"/>
                     <q>
                        <l>As if <hi>Confeſſion</hi> had catcht</l>
                        <l>The itch, on purpoſe to be ſcratcht;</l>
                     </q> OR
<q>
                        <l>As if <hi>Confeſſion</hi> were intended,</l>
                        <l>For nothing elſe, but to be mended.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>They think that if they exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine no longer, they shall be mightily diſturb'd in mind; and they always find, that the longer they examine, the more they are diſturb'd. They trouble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for fear of being troubled: and by their willfull diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in this very point, they loſe God's favour, for fear of loſing it. An extravagancy much like that, which the <hi>Poet</hi> deſcribes, of one <hi>Fannius,</hi> who took the pains to kill himſelf, for fear his Enemy should ſave him the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, &amp; do it for him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <note n="(h)" place="bottom">Hoſtem dum fugeret, ſe <hi>Fannius</hi> ipſe peremit: Dic mihi, quis furor eſt, ne moriare, mori?</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:43611:19"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>He fled from death, &amp; kill'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in flying:</l>
                     <l>What madneſs is't, to die for fear of dying?</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III. <hi>The extravagancy of their Fears.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WHereas the Duties of Temperance extend themſelves alike to all particular matters which regard our health, and conſequently oblige us to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a proportionable equality &amp; regularity in all our meaſures: On the contrary, theſe proud Penitents are unequal &amp; irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular in every thing. They are terribly fearfull, where they need not fear; and where there is moſt danger, they are leaſt concern'd for't. Exceſſively ſollicitous in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43611:20"/>the Examen of their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and ſupinely careleſs in the Amendment of their lives.</p>
                  <p>They are frighted into a dread full apprehenſion of ſome trifles, which are little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to their purpoſe; and whilſt they are ſo ſtedfaſtly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive to theſe needleſs points, they are inſenſible &amp; ſtupid as to all things elſe. They <hi>will</hi> be their own <hi>Guides;</hi> &amp; by God's juſt judgment upon them, they are <hi>blind</hi> ones. They are like the <hi>blind Guides</hi> in the Goſpel,
<note n="(i)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 23.24.</note> 
                     <hi>who ſtrein at a gnat, &amp; ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> a <hi>Camel.</hi> They ſtartle at eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inconſiderable difficulty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by their own imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and, in things of great importance, go on as boldly &amp; as unconcerndly as if they did not ſee Hell gaping under their feet.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43611:20"/>Their ſtomach riſes at the very thought of reſigning their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in doubtfull caſes; and in things which are undoubtedly hurtfull, even to the degree of poyſonous, they ſit down to them with a very good appetite. All the Severities of exteriour mortification, as watchings, faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, hair-cloths, and the like, are commonly wellcome to them: becauſe they are well enough pleaſed with any thing that feeds their pride, &amp; helps them to a falſe perſwaſion of their being in the high road of the Saints. Theſe things they'l practiſe, even when their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor forbids them. But, as for the
<note n="(k)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.23.</note> 
                     <hi>renewing of their Spirit</hi> and <hi>their Mind,</hi> the beſt &amp; moſt important mortification, which is that of the Soul, by croſſing of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43611:21"/>their humour &amp; ſubmitting of their judgment, They hate the very thought of it: Not a word of that; as you love them. If all this be not extravagant, Pray tell me, What is?</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>The pernicious Conſequences of the ſame Scrupuloſity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF people might play the fool, as they pleaſe, in the way to Heaven, without being ever the worſe for it: then indeed the Scrupuloſity, I ſpeak of, would be an innocent ſort of Folly, without any Miſchief in it. But ſurely, if what we believe of Heaven &amp; Hell be true, there can be nothing more pernicious &amp; more fatal to us, than that ſturdy &amp; reſty Scrupuloſity, which will neither lead nor
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43611:21"/>drive, but will be always either ſtanding ſtill, or looking back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, to obſerve the way behind it. At this rate of going to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, How is it poſſible for us ever to get thither?</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Paul</hi> compares the way to Heaven, to the running of a race, in which we ſtrive to win the prize of everlaſting Glory. Conſider onely what a diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage it is for a man to look be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him all the way he runs. Without queſtion he who looks before him, advances with much more eaſe, much greater ſpeed, &amp; much leſs danger: whereas he who looks behind him, muſt needs move very ſlowly &amp; uneaſily, beſides being expoſed every moment to a double dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, either of falling, or of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his way. If theſe people thought the way to Heaven eaſy,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43611:22"/>they would not be ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid as they are: and, if they think it hard to find, why are they always gazing backwards? The way lies before them; and looking forward is the ſureſt way to find it.</p>
               <p>Our Saviour bids us
<note n="(l)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Luke.</hi> 13.24.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrait Gate: for many will ſeek to enter in, &amp; shall not be able.</hi> We muſt <hi>ſtrive to enter:</hi> We muſt not loſe time: we muſt make what haſt we can: &amp; how can we make haſt, if we are always looking behind us? Beſides, the <hi>Gate</hi> is <hi>ſtrait:</hi> If it were wide enough, one might hit it without aiming at it: but, being ſo <hi>ſtrait</hi> as it is, if we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways looking behind us, 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to hit it. And therefore 'tis no wonder that our Saviour adds, <hi>Many will ſtrive to enter in,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43611:22"/>&amp; shall not be able:</hi> becauſe many will be always puzzling their brains with making, or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, their general confeſſions; &amp; always looking whence they come, without minding whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her they go.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I. <hi>The difference betwixt Servile Fear and Loving Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ONe of the principal cauſes from whence this great diſorder proceeds, is
<note n="(m)" place="bottom">nimiustim or ſervilis, quem ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerat nimiusamor proprius, quemque diminuit perfecta charitas, ex quâ &amp; ex timore filialirarò naſcitur haec affectio. <hi>Suaraz</hi> 1.2. diſp. 12. ſect. ult. n. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of ſervile Fear;</hi> and 'tis a thouſand pities they are ſo much over-power'd with it. Tis true;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43611:23"/>
                     <hi>Fear</hi> is good; &amp; 'tis
<note n="(n)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.10.</note> 
                     <hi>the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of wiſdom:</hi> But what is the Beginning good for, if it never bring them to the End?
<note n="(o)" place="bottom">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5.</note> 
                     <hi>The end of the Law is Love.</hi> When ſervile Fear is grown to a very great exceſs, 'tis like the winter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſon of the Soul; 'tis a certain chillineſs of Love, which makes them quake &amp; tremble, whether they will or no. If they had but time to breath a while; if they had any reſpite to conſider the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Goodneſs; if their continual fears would give them leaſure to
<note n="(p)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Pſal</hi> 39.9.</note> 
                     <hi>taſt &amp; ſee how ſweet God is;</hi> the <hi>Love</hi> of him would ſoon im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove in their hearts; it would be like the Sun's approaching nigher their Meridian; it would warm them, quicken them, &amp; drive away the chilly coldneſs of their <hi>Fear.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:43611:23"/>
                  <p>True Friendship naturally inſpires a loving Confidence in our Friend. The more we love him, the more we confide in him. And if we love him very much, we are apt to have ſo much confidence in him, as to think it almoſt impoſſible for him to find in his heart to hurt us. If this be ſo, even amongſt us mortals, notwithſtanding our ill nature &amp; our being ſubject to miſtake, ſurely the ſelf-ſame reaſon is of much more force, when 'tis applied to God. Our friends on earth may be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, &amp; ſuſpect our love; or elſe may poſſibly be ſo illnatur'd as to ſlight it, though they know it. But our God can neither be illnatur'd to us, nor mistaken in us: if we love him, we may be aſſured, he always knows it, and he never ſlights it.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:43611:24"/>
                  <p>Tis S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Maxim: <hi>Love, &amp; Do what you will.</hi> Do but <hi>love</hi> God, and whatever you <hi>do,</hi> under the direction &amp; influence of this Love, will never diſturb your peace. Do but <hi>love</hi> him heartily, and then you will never purpoſely and deliberately deſign to offend him: your chief deſign will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be to pleaſe him: and, whatſoever frailties or ſurpriſes happen, as long as this deſign ſubſiſts, you need not doubt but that they always will be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable. Do but <hi>love</hi> him above all things, and all your imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, whatſoêre they are, will onely ſerve to humble you, they never will incline you to deſpair.</p>
                  <p>S. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us, that
<note n="(p)" place="bottom">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.8.</note> 
                     <hi>Love covers a multitude of faults.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43611:24"/>onely the imperfections of little children: how frequent, &amp; how troubleſome they are: And yet the tenderneſs of any loving Parent <hi>covers</hi> all. Theſe children are dutifull in the main: they love their Parents better than any other friends: and are ſorry for nothing more than for offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them. On the other ſide, their Parents, who ſee it, are ſatisfied in the main: They are content to bear with other dayly failings: They correct &amp; chide them for their leſſer faults: But, though they are frequently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd, there is no danger of their children being disinherited. The more we ſee, &amp; the more clearly we diſcover, the guilt of all our dayly trespaſſes, the more we ought to humble our ſelves in preſence of our God, and love him ſo much more for lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43611:25"/>us in ſpite of all our faults, and for aſſuring us that if our Love perſever to the end, we shall never loſe our right to the inheritance of Heaven. Is not this enough to moderate &amp; govern all our fears? What need we wish for more?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II. <hi>The miſchief of long Examens.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IF Scrupulous people would but find a little leaſure to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider ſeriously ſuch comfortable truths as theſe, they would ſoon find benefit by them: but their miſchief is, they have always ſomething elſe to do, when they should think <hi>how good</hi> God is. Inſtead of calling to mind how kind &amp; tender a <hi>Father</hi> they have <hi>in Heaven,</hi> their buſy thoughts
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43611:25"/>are entertain'd with fancies of his being a ſevere &amp; cruel <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> upon <hi>Earth.</hi> A Tyrant that exacts more from them than their utmoſt diligence is able to perform: an Enemy that always watches to deſtroy them, &amp; delights in laying hold of any opportunity to ruine them: a Maſter ſo intolerably rigid in exacting his accounts, that when his Slaves have done whatever they can, 'tis all in vain, there is no poſſibility of ever making even reckonings with him. I will not ſay, they abſolutely <hi>are</hi> of this opinion: but this I am ſure of, they behave themſelves as if they <hi>were.</hi> Tis hard to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine what opinion they are of; or whether they have any opinion at all. The onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture which I dare rely upon, is this: that where their Fears pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43611:26"/>they are little better (if not worſe) than Infidels. They dare not believe the Church of God, nor even God himſelf: and therefore 'tis no wonder, if they dare not truſt their Confeſſor.</p>
                  <p>The Word of God himſelf aſſures them in general, that
<note n="(q)" place="bottom">1. <hi>Jo.</hi> 5.3.</note> 
                     <hi>his Commands are not grievous:</hi> and yet they cannot believe it. They think the obligation of confeſſing is the moſt grievous thing imaginable; &amp; that 'tis morally impoſſible to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd with.</p>
                  <p>The Council of <hi>Trent</hi> aſſures them in particular, that <hi>this</hi> Command <hi>is not grievous.</hi> It de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, that
<note n="(r)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Seſs.</hi> 14. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> 
                     <hi>it is an impious thing,</hi> either <hi>to ſay it is impoſſible, or to call it a Torture of Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> They do not believe this neither. They find by experience
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:43611:26"/>that their Spirits are upon the wrack, &amp; that it is a <hi>Torture</hi> to them, whenſoever they prepare for Confeſſion. Tis true; it is their own fault, who are willfull in over-doing their duty. But this is another truth, which they believe no more than the reſt. They are too proud to blame themſelves; and therefore lay the fault upon their obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>The Council declares that
<note n="(s)" place="bottom">conſtat enim, nihil, aliud in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia à poenitentibus exigi, quàm ut poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam quiſque diligentius ſe excuſſerit ea peccata confiteatur, quibus ſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum &amp; Deum ſuum mortaliter of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendiſſe meminerit: reliqua autem pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata, quae diligenter cogitanti non oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currunt, in univerſum, eâdem Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione incluſa eſſe intelliguntur. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>NOTHING MORE is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the Church from Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents, than that after a DI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIGENT
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43611:27"/>EXAMEN every one confeſs thoſe ſins in which THEY REMEMBER them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to have offended mortally the Lord their God: &amp; that THE REST of their Sins,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they are, <hi>which after a diligent examen DO NOT occur to mind, are ALL underſtood to be INCLUDED in the ſame Confeſſion.</hi> This Declaration would be as comfortable as their hearts can wish, if they did but believe it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nothing more</hi> is <hi>required,</hi> than to confeſs thoſe Sins which <hi>they remember;</hi> not which they <hi>can,</hi> but which they <hi>do</hi> remember. From when it plainly follows, that, if they <hi>do not</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, they are altogether as ſecure as if they <hi>could not.</hi> If we we were obliged to examine till we remember <hi>all;</hi> then indeed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:43611:27"/>our proud Penitents, who will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully torture themſelves with long &amp; tedious examens, would be very much in the right of it: But, on the contrary, 'tis evident the Council does not oblige us to <hi>remember;</hi> it onely obliges us to <hi>examine.</hi> Neither is it in the power of any Council to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a man, to have a good memory: but, ſuch as it is, a good one, or a bad one, we are commanded to be diligent in calling it to an account. This done, We neither are the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if we remember <hi>all,</hi> nor worſe, if we forget the <hi>greateſt part.</hi> If we remember our ſins exactly, <hi>all</hi> &amp; <hi>everyone</hi> of them, What greater advantage can we expect, than to have them <hi>all</hi> &amp; <hi>every one</hi> forgiven us? This is certainly All: &amp; this advantage is the very ſame, to all intents &amp;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:43611:28"/>purpoſes of pardon, although we forget the <hi>greateſt part,</hi> becauſe the Council has declared, they are <hi>all</hi> forgiven as fully &amp; as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely as if we had remember'd &amp; confeſs'd them.</p>
                  <p>To what purpoſe then is all this torturing of their minds, when it manifeſtly does more harm than good? It diſturbs their thoughts, it robs them of their peace, it dries up their devotion, it deprives them of all comfort, it renders them exceſſively uneaſy, it tempts &amp; leads them to impatience &amp; deſpair.</p>
                  <p>To what purpoſe is all this pudder of examining? Is it to pleaſe God, or your ſelf? To pleaſe your ſelf, is a dangerous buſineſs: for, although your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience may be pleaſing here, 'tis much to be fear'd the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment of it will be very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:43611:28"/>hereafter. And, as for pleaſing God, 'tis certain he is equally pleas'd, when he has equally forgiven us: and the Council aſſures us, He equally forgives what we forget, &amp; as perfectly, as what we remember.</p>
                  <p>Let us now compare the doctrine of the Council, with the practice of theſe people. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their practice, there is nothing more neceſſary than this <hi>endleſs diligence:</hi> and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Council, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more needleſs. From whence I leave you to conclude, whether or no theſe examining creatures are thoſe who <hi>hear the Church,</hi> or whether they are not in ſome danger of being, one day, reckon'd amongſt the <hi>Heathens</hi> &amp; the <hi>Publicans.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:43611:29"/>
                  <head>SECT. III. <hi>Blind Obedience the beſt Remedy.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AN humble Penitent is free from theſe diſorders. His ſcrupuloſity may be fearfull; 'tis the nature of it to be ſo: but it never is incurable: becauſe 'tis truly humble &amp; ſubmiſſive. The remedies of it are always at hand; And, with his Confeſſor's advice, he is always ready to apply them. His Confeſſor needs onely ſay the word; he never asks a reaſon <hi>why.</hi> He has a general reaſon for all doubtfull caſes whatſoever; a reaſon which he always carries about with him; an everlaſting reaſon which is ever the ſame, &amp; which he is infallibly aſſured of, that <hi>in doubtfull caſes nothing is ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:43611:29"/>as Obedience.</hi> He never has any troubleſome doubts, to vex him or moleſt him. He knows for certain, what he is bid do, &amp; <hi>that</hi> he does, without ever doubting of it. He fears nothing but himſelf; he fears his frailty; he fears his being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient: Theſe are the onely things he fears: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is fearfull without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, carefull without anxiety, &amp; diligent without any trouble. He is as dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in the examen of his Conſcience, as men of buſineſs are in any ſerious affair. More than this, he is not obliged to: and ſo much as this, is as eaſy to him, as it is ordinary to every body elſe. He is ſo humble, as to enquire of his Confeſſor, what length of time he pleaſes to allow for his examen; and ſo obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:43611:30"/>that he has no inclination to exceed his allowance. He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins his work, goes on with it, &amp; ends it, all with the ſame eaſe.</p>
                  <p>He knows very well that the general reaſon of his Obedience is grounded upon as firm a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, as the <hi>rock</hi> it ſelf, upon which the <hi>Church</hi> is built: and therefore he never enquires after any particular reaſons, <hi>why</hi> his Confeſſor allows him no more time. He not onely deſpiſes all theſe curioſities, but even hates them: becauſe he firmly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves, they are as pernicious as they are ſuperfluous. Nor is it any wonder he believes it, if it be true, that <hi>ſeeing</hi> is <hi>believing;</hi> for he plainly <hi>ſees</hi> the ſad expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of it, in his proud &amp; will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full neighbours, who are never quiet, but are always reſtleſs &amp; uneaſy; never contented, but
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:43611:30"/>always labouring in vain to build Security upon the ſandy foundation of their own weak Reaſon. A Foundation which is never firm; but either flies like duſt before each puff of Wind, or elſe is washt away, &amp; chang'd with every Tide.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Nothing more unreaſonable than a boundleſs Liberty of reaſoning.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT happens very unluckily for us, that the chief Faculty we have, which God has given us to govern all the reſt, is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the moſt ungovernable of them all: and that our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which calls them all to an account, is ſometimes the moſt unaccountable it ſelf. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:43611:31"/>ſays
<note n="(t)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.34.35.</note> 
                  <hi>Salt is good: but if the Salt have loſt its ſavour, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with shall it be ſeaſon'd? It is neither fit for the Land, nor for the Dunghill, but men caſt it out.</hi> In the ſame manner, Reaſon is good: 'tis good, to overſee our Appetites, our words, &amp; Actions: 'tis good, to watch them, &amp; to keep them within the bounds of Temperance &amp; Moderation: 'tis good, to ſummon them before the Bar, examine, reprehend, &amp; punish them for their tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: All this, right Reaſon is good for. But if our Reaſon it ſelf be the greateſt tranſgreſſor, the moſt intemperate, the moſt extravagant of all; What is it good for, but to be <hi>caſt out</hi> of doors, and
<note n="(u)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 5.13.</note> 
                  <hi>troden under foot by men?</hi> This, I confeſs, is a hard ſaying; a ſevere Sentence:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:43611:31"/>but yet, by what has been alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſaid, it plainly appears, it is not more ſevere than it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves.</p>
               <p>Humane Reaſon is the beſt thing in Nature, if rightly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged; &amp; the worſt, if a proud willfull creature have the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. Tis commonly ſaid, that <hi>Pride will have a fall:</hi> Nor is it any wonder, if it be always true; becauſe it looks too high to ſee the way before it. Tis like the Philoſopher who fell into a ditch whilſt he was gazing at the Stars. The Reaſon which God has given us, if rightly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd, would make us humble &amp; ſubmiſſive; it would open our eyes, to ſee how fallible we are; &amp; open our ears to hear the advice of others, who are wiſer than our ſelves. But, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, when Reaſon is abuſed,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:43611:32"/>&amp; ill applied, it makes us proud &amp; willfull: it puffs us up with a vain eſteem of our own judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; &amp; the higher it raiſes us, the greater fall it gives us.</p>
               <p>The fall of our firſt Parents had an influence upon the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding as well as the Will of their poſterity: and a great part of our original diſeaſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in an inſatiable Curioſity, by which we aim at being <hi>like the Higheſt.</hi> We would know all things, and have a reaſon for every thing. This is the deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate condition of thoſe ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous perſons, to whom I here addreſs my ſelf. They are brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick with too much reaſoning. They thirſt after reaſon, as dropſical people after drink: and, the more you give them, the more you encreaſe the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper. Reaſon without ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:43611:32"/>is the very thing which makes them ſick: and nothing will ever cure them, but an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Submiſſion, in all doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full caſes, without any particular reaſons for it. Their Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding raves continually after an infinity of idle &amp; unneceſſary notions: and, to make it ſober, there is nothing like darkening the windows; for, whileſt you let the light break in upon it, you will never bring it to it ſelf.</p>
               <p>At this rate, you'l ſay, God gave us our Reaſon to little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; if, in doubtfull caſes, it be better to reſign it, than to uſe it. I beg your pardon. Our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is given us, to as much pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as our other Faculties are: It is given us, to make right uſe of it; and not to enjoy the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of it at our own diſcretion.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:43611:33"/>We are as much obliged to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Rules of Temperance in reaſoning, as in eating &amp; drinking: and our Curioſity of knowing too much is oftentimes as dangerous as either Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony or Drunkenneſs. There are many things which are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for us to eat: and there are many more, which are as impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for us to know. But a proud Mind is like a depraved Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, &amp; both are moſt inclined to what is moſt pernicious to them. Such was the diſeaſe of our firſt Parents, which ſtill runs in the blood of the whole Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. They had <hi>knowledg</hi> enough to ſerve their turn, but were not contented with it: they were cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to try the experiment of what was meant by <hi>knowing good &amp; evil:</hi> they <hi>knew</hi> it to their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, &amp; paid dearly for it. A
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:43611:33"/>little Blind Obedience would have kept them in the ſtate of Innocence: but, to obey with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a particular reaſon <hi>why,</hi> was more than they were willing to ſupport. They would not endure to be kept in any degree of Darkneſs. Their inſatiable Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity allow'd no terms of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration to their Uſe of Reaſon. They would have <hi>their eyes ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:</hi> they would <hi>be as Gods:</hi> they would either know All or Nothing. See here an early ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Intemperance of Humane Reaſon. See how ſpeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ily, &amp; how ſeverely it was pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish'd. And learn from thence this uſefull Leſſon; that we are as much obliged to obſerve the rules of Temperance in Uſing of our Reaſon, as we are to keep a Moderation &amp; Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum in the Uſe of meat &amp; drink.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:43611:34"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>All or Nothing,</hi> is the Motto of a Libertin. All that lies in his way, is lawfull to him. <hi>What was it All made for?</hi> What was He himſelf created for, but to <hi>enjoy</hi> the faculties which Nature has beſtow'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him? He values no other <hi>uſe</hi> than the <hi>enjoyment</hi> of them. When he plays the Glutton, or the Drunkard, &amp;c. he juſtifies himſelf with asking, <hi>Is it not lawfull for a man to eat, &amp; drink, &amp;c. What were All theſe things made for?</hi> What were his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites &amp; Reaſon made for, but to pick &amp; chuſe, love &amp; hate, think &amp; do, whatêre he pleaſes? The thinking part of him (which is a thing he ſcarce knows what to think of) ſeems capable of knowing All things: and <hi>Why should any Laws of God or Man pretend to limit it?</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:43611:34"/>So unreaſonable is the Uſe of Humane Reaſon, when it is a Slave to Pride &amp; Willfullneſs which commonly are the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers &amp; diſpoſers of it! <hi>My Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is my own,</hi> ſay they; <hi>God did not give it me for nothing. What matter is't, how dark &amp; doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full theſe things are? My Reaſon is my Judge. My boundleſs Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is capable of knowing All things: Why should any body ſtint it?</hi> The proud &amp; boiſtrous Sea when it ſwells high, &amp; with a full tide rushes in upon the shore, if it could ſpeak, might ſay the ſame thing with as good a grace: <hi>My boundleſs waves are able to oreflow the Earth: and Why should I ſtop here?</hi> Proud Creatures! Tis in vain to lift up your rebellious hands againſt the Hand that made you;
<note n="(w)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.5.</note>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:43611:35"/>
                  <hi>Though hand joyn in hand, you shall not be unpunish'd.</hi> He who has
<note n="(x)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Job.</hi> 38.8.11.</note> 
                  <hi>shut up the Sea with doors, &amp; ſaid, Here shall thy proud waves be ſtay'd;</hi> He, I ſay has shut up Humane Reaſon within the compaſs of its Duty, &amp; ſaid, <hi>Hitherto shalt thou come, but no further.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>The difference betwixt a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher &amp; a Chriſtian, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Submiſſion of Humane Reaſon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Liberties of natural Reaſon are as large as thoſe of Nature it ſelf: &amp; as we know no certain bounds of natural cauſes &amp; effects, ſo we preſcribe no limits to our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:43611:35"/>Reaſon in endeavouring to diſcover them. All this viſible World, &amp; even the Maker of it (ſo far as we can trace his footſteps, &amp; <hi>underſtand</hi> him <hi>by the things</hi> which he has <hi>made</hi>) are the object &amp; the ſubject of our ſpeculations. Tis like a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Delight, where Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Reaſon may divert it ſelf; &amp; ramble up and down without ever finding any end of it. Tis a place of Pleaſure, where a Philoſopher dayly meets with fresh diſcoveries of entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his curioſity, which is the onely greedy Appetite he has. His buſineſs does not lie in Action, but in Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation: and, in this reſpect, he may truly ſay, the Natural World is all his own: He may <hi>think,</hi> &amp; <hi>judge,</hi> &amp; <hi>reaſon,</hi> as he pleaſes, concerning all, &amp; every part, of it.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:43611:36"/>
               <p>The Supernatural World is quite another thing. The great &amp; glorious End, which all good Chriſtians aim at, is Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural: and to make our natural reaſon the ſupreme Judge of matters relating to this End, is a thing manifeſtly unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For, although it be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable in a Philoſopher, to take nothing upon truſt, it would be evidently unpardonable in a Chriſtian. Of all the four laſt things, which Chriſtians ought to <hi>remember</hi> that they may <hi>never ſin;</hi> Death is the onely thing we naturally are aſſured of. No bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy's natural reaſon can demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate what we believe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Judgment, Hell, or Heaven. And yet, to prepare for this Judgment, to avoid this Hell, &amp; to enjoy this Heaven, a good Chriſtian ſacrifices all things
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:43611:36"/>here, his fortune, his life, his friends, &amp; whatſoever is moſt dear to him. At the approach of Death, he reſigns his Spirit into the hands of God: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he does not <hi>ſee</hi> in <hi>what</hi> his future Happineſs conſiſts; he puts his Confidence in God, who has reveal'd his Mercies to us; and in the Church, who has aſſured us of his Promiſes. He joyfully relies upon theſe great aſſurances of more than he is able to conceive: and is content to take them upon truſt.</p>
               <p>I do not wonder, that no body is worthy of Heaven, who dares not take God's word for it. But this I admire, that they who can truſt God with their Souls, with their Eternity, with their unſeen &amp; unknown hopes of Happineſs in Heaven; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs cannot ſubmit ſo far,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:43611:37"/>as to truſt him with their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct upon Earth, &amp; to rely upon the Guides which he has given them. If we can follow God ſo cheerfully into an unſeen World: Why can we not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him as cheerfully through an unknown Way? The Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſurely is the greateſt in the End: and, if we can truſt him when we part from hence, I know no reaſon why we may not truſt him all the while we are here.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>The different Sentiments of a Proud &amp; an Humble Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, concerning Blind Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAppy are they who are blindly Obedient, without
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:43611:37"/>demurring, reaſoning, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting. They are embarkt in a Veſſell, where they may ſleep ſecure: they need not take any further care, they have <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> for their Pilot. All that we receive from God, we ought to Sacrifice to him; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently our Underſtanding as well as our Will. If we fail in this one point, our being exact in all the reſt will ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie little or nothing. The fall of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> &amp; his companions, is a ſufficient proof. They were Angels in all other reſpects, and never had been Devils, if they had ſubmitted their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding &amp; their Will to him who made them. That Pride which alone was enough to caſt the Angels out of Heaven, That alone, though we were Angels in all things
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:43611:38"/>elſe, is enough to hinder us from ever going thither. Our beſt way to ſecure our ſelves, &amp; to diſcover the artifices of an Enemy who is as cunning as he is malicious, is to look upon Obedience as the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of all the vertue and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which we aim at. The Devil can counterfeit all other vertues, but he could never counterfeit Obedience. Had he at firſt ſubmitted his Will &amp; Underſtanding to his great Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior, who made him; had he but been Obedient while he was an Angel, he had never been a Devil. If Obedience be our Rule, in all our Actions, &amp; in all the circumſtances of them; if it be our dayly buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to improve &amp; grow more perfect in complying with this Rule; it is impoſſible that we
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:43611:38"/>should ever erre. We cannot but know what we are bid to do; and, if we know that, we know the high-way to Heaven: Let us onely do as we are bid, and we shall certainly go thit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her. As long as the Sheep fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their Shepherd, they are ſafe: but, if any of them go aſtray from the Flock, 'tis no wonder they are devoured by the Wolves.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the Sentiments of an humble Penitent. But they who are proud and willfull, are not ſo eaſily ſatisfied con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe matters. The very thought of Blind Obedience is like news of death, to their beloved Curioſity, &amp; darling Humour, which they are ſo deſperately fond of. If Death it ſelf should come within their view, &amp; shew his Sythe, and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:43611:39"/>onely ſome few Sands at the bottom of the Glaſs, it would not chill their Spirits more than it does to think their Curioſity muſt be buried alive, &amp; their Humour lie as low as duſt, without ever riſing again. If they were truly Penitent, the Spirit of Repentance would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire a holy revenge in punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe Faculties of the Soul, which were the inſtruments of Sin. They would punish their Will, by reſtraining it in things which are indifferent, &amp; mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie their Underſtanding, by reſigning it in matters which are doubtfull. If they conſider'd ſeriouſly the extravagancies which attend their Pride &amp; Curioſity, and the pernicious conſequences of their Willfull Humour, they would hate them now, as much as heretofore
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:43611:39"/>they loved them: they would not ſuffer them ſo much as to ſee the Light, which they are ſo unworthy of, but willingly condemn them to the Darkneſs of a Dungeon, during life. Tis a ſevere Sentence: But what have you to ſay againſt it, that it may not paſs?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What am I the better for my Reaſon, if I may not act accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In doubtfull caſes, you never act more conformably to your own right reaſon, than when you renounce the probability of your Speculations, &amp; ſubmit them to your Judge without rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning the matter with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Confeſſor may be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Very well: He may ſo. But does not God know <hi>that</hi> as well as you? And yet he has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:43611:40"/>him to be your Judge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I really believe he is miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may believe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, if you pleaſe; as long as you are not <hi>certain</hi> of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have a great many reaſons to think him in the wrong, and no particular reaſon to think him in the right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Put all your <hi>reaſons</hi> in one Scale: put his <hi>Authority</hi> in the other: And, if it have as much weight with you as it ought to have, 'twill over weigh them all. His Authority is from God: Your reaſons, which tempt you to deſpiſe it, are no better than Suggeſtions of the Devil. His Authority is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely certain &amp; ſecure: Your reaſons (if there happen to be any reaſon in them) are but doubtfull &amp; uncertain. Put all
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:43611:40"/>this together: Conſider it well: And you will ſoon be asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of diſputing ſuch matters any longer with your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not This being what they call Prieſt-ridden?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Wits of our profane Age are pleaſed to call it ſo. But ſome people are too witty, to be wiſe. Their buſineſs is not ſo much to underſtand any thing, as to laugh at all things. Whatever comes in their way, if it furnish matter for a jeſt, they take no further care. They have a merry time, while it laſts. But, when their Life's in danger, there are none more tractable in the hands of a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician: They'l be <hi>Doctor-ridden</hi> as much as you pleaſe. Nay, if it be onely their Eſtate which is in jeopardy, They'l be <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer-ridden</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:43611:41"/>too. They pin their their faith upon their Lawyer's ſleeve. They argue not the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with him. They ſuffer not their Reaſon to come in compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition with his Skill. He tell's them, <hi>This is Law.</hi> They do not conceive <hi>how</hi> it comes to be ſo. It ſeems unreaſonable to them. And yet they believe him: they ſubmit: and blindly follow his Advice. Beſides, when all is done, they are <hi>Judge-ridden</hi> whether they will or no; and neither dare nor can complain of it: becauſe they know very well, that no body is fit to live under any Form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, who will not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to ſuch Judges as are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Law. And truly, with all ſubmiſſion to his Majeſty, I ſee no reaſon why we ought not to have ſome reſpect for <hi>God</hi>'s
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:43611:41"/>Judges, as well as for the <hi>King</hi>'s.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>A Scripture-Objection anſwer'd.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TIs written in Scripture, that
<note n="(y)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 15.14.</note> 
                  <hi>if the Blind lead the Blind, they both fall into the Ditch.</hi> But however, this Text, if rightly underſtood, is no good argument againſt Blind Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
               <p n="1">I. If <hi>both</hi> are innocently <hi>blind,</hi> 'tis certain that neither of them will fall into the pit of <hi>Hell,</hi> which here is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the <hi>Ditch.</hi> Becauſe the Divine Juſtice cannot pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Innocency, or condemn the Blindneſs of thoſe who are not guilty of it.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:43611:42"/>
               <p n="2">II. If a Confeſſor be proud &amp; careleſs, ſo as to be guilty of his Blindneſs, nevertheleſs the Penitents who (in doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full matters) humbly &amp; ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely follow his Advice, will never be punish'd for his fault, but be rewarded for obeying him. Tis written in Scripture that the Soul which commits the Sin, the ſame shall die; and no, other shall ſuffer, either for it, or with it. The words are plain;
<note n="(z)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.20.</note> 
                  <hi>The Soul that ſinneth, it shall die: The Son shall not bear the iniquity of the Father, but the wickedneſs of the wicked</hi> Father <hi>shall be upon him</hi> onely. From whence it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently follows, that although the Ghoſtly Father be willfully and wickedly Blind, yet all Sincere &amp; Humble Penitents
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:43611:42"/>(in all their doubts) may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently &amp; ſecurely ſubmit to him: becauſe, not being part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of his Guilt, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly be made partakers of his Punishment.</p>
               <p n="3">III. If <hi>both</hi> are criminally <hi>blind;</hi> that is, if they love dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, if they shut their eyes againſt the light, if they are blind becauſe they have no mind to ſee, in a word, if they are proud &amp; willfull, as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> &amp; their <hi>Diſciples</hi> were; Then indeed, they <hi>both</hi> deſerve to <hi>fall into the Ditch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For example: You have no mind to obey your Confeſſor, &amp; therefore you will not believe him: You have a mind to follow your own humour, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you hearken to thoſe little reaſons, which you ſeem to have for it. In this caſe, you
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:43611:43"/>you are not ſincere, you are partial in your own favour: you are more willing to believe your ſelf than to believe your Guide, &amp; more deſirous to pleaſe your ſelf than to pleaſe God. This is the willfull part of your Blindneſs. Let us now conſider the pride of it it. You are naturally curious in what belongs to you: you are <hi>wiſe in your own conceit,</hi> &amp; puff'd up with the thought of being ſo: you think it very hard for any body elſe to underſtand you better than you underſtand your ſelf, &amp; therefore you value your own judgment too much, &amp; your Confeſſor's too little. But yet your Pride and Willfullneſs are no excuſe for your Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. One fault is no excuſe for another. Your willfull Pride is a notorious fault: 'tis viſible
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:43611:43"/>to every body elſe: and, if it did not blind you, it would be viſible to your ſelf. Tis in your power to be humble &amp; ſubmiſſive, if you pleaſe. Tis a vertue, which if you ſeriouſly endeavour to practiſe, God will help you: and, if you heartily beg it of him, he will not fail to give it you. Mean time, as blind as you are, you are not ſo thoroughly confident of your own opinion, but that you would be glad to have it ſeconded by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of your Guide. For this reaſon, you are ſo eager to diſcourſe with him; not to know his mind, but to let him know yours: not to ſubmit to what he ſays, but to make him ſubſcribe to what you think: not to learn his opinion, but to teach him your own. If
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:43611:44"/>you cannot prevail; you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult another; and another: And your buſineſs is to find, either a Guide that will be guided by you (which is no Guide at all) or elſe a Guide as much miſtaken as your ſelf, who is contented to lead you your own way; and then, to be ſure, your Blindneſs will not excuſe you, becauſe 'tis your own fault from the beginning to the end. Had you humbly &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely relied upon the Guide which Providence appointed you, You had been certain, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be in the right way, or to be blameleſs, if in the wrong. But ſince you proudly &amp; willfully left a Guide <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to God's heart,</hi> to take another according to your own, You ſought for darkneſs, &amp; for your punishment you found
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:43611:44"/>it: and then indeed, you may be ſure, if your Blind Guide <hi>fall in to the Ditch,</hi> you'l fall in after him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Pretences of Reaſon anſwerd.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ONe would think, the bare conſideration of the follies &amp; the miſchiefs which attend the pride &amp; willfulneſs of weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; comparing every tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling reaſon <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> in every doubtfull matter, One would think, I ſay, that this alone were more than abundantly ſufficient to ſatisfie any reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able perſon, that nothing is more rational, than to ſilence theſe impertinent reaſons, &amp; to turn them out of doors. I am ſure there is very good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:43611:45"/>for it: and, if Reaſon does it, 'tis enough; the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Blind Obedience have no reaſon to complain.</p>
               <p>And yet 'tis commonly their cuſtom, not onely to complain but to object a great many odious things againſt it, which look as if they were a little ſpitefull in miſrepreſenting it. <hi>Has not God given us our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? Are we not accountable to him for it? And are we not bound in Duty to make the beſt uſe we can of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tis eaſily anſwer'd: We cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly are ſo: and becauſe our blind Submiſſion is grounded upon the beſt Reaſon we have, therefore 'tis certain that we make the beſt uſe we can of it, when we blindly ſubmit. Tis true; if a man pretended to banish all reaſon whatſoever,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:43611:45"/>&amp; to ſubmit himſelf univerſally without any manner of reaſon for it; Then, I muſt, needs confeſs, our blind Submiſſion would be the moſt unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing in the world. But this is never practiſed or adviſed by any that I ever heard of.</p>
               <p>Whenſoever we ſubmit our <hi>ſpeculative</hi> reaſons to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of a Confeſſor, 'tis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways under the conduct &amp; influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of our chief <hi>practical</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which is ſuperior to them, &amp; has a legal juriſdiction over them. Our <hi>ſpeculations</hi> are num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſs: and, in deciding doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full matters, if we give them audience, our labour is in vain. For, either we hear them all together, &amp; then there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but confuſion: or elſe we hear them one by one, &amp; then there is no end of them. Our
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:43611:46"/>
                  <hi>practical</hi> notions lie within a little compaſs: they are given us by God himſelf as rules of life &amp; action: they are few, and eaſily underſtood; they are plain, &amp; eaſily applied; and, which is beſt of all, the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them is every jot as ſafe, as the underſtanding &amp; applying of them are eaſie. Theſe practical principles are the beſt Reaſon of Mankind. By theſe, in wordly affairs we behave our ſelves like Men; and by the ſame, in ſpiritual matters, we act like Chriſtians; And therefore, if by theſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry principles we ſuſpend &amp; ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence all thoſe needleſs ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, which are onely fit to trouble &amp; moleſt us; if we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them to retire; and order them to give place to Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: Where is the harm? Can
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:43611:46"/>you blame us for following the beſt Reaſon we have, &amp; making the beſt uſe we can of it? When a man takes aim, &amp; shuts one eye; you may ſay, he's blind, if you pleaſe: but the truth is, he onely winks with the left eye, that he may ſee much better with the right.</p>
               <p>If this were well conſiderd, it would pacifie a little the minds of thoſe people, who purſue ſo fiercely their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to a boundleſs liberty of reaſoning. They would ſoon diſcover, not onely that the Obedience, which I plead for, is not ſo blind as they are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to repreſent it; but alſo that it allows them as much li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty as any reaſonable man can wish for.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In things which are evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:43611:47"/>or abſolutely certain, no body queſtions but that our Reaſon has free room to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe it ſelf without reſtraint. No body ever goes to a Confeſſor to conſult him, whether or no they ought to believe their Creed; whether the ſeven deadly ſins be lawfull or not; or whether the ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ought to be obſerved. They have no need of troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their Guides about thoſe things which every body knows that all the Catholick world agrees in.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In matters which are dark and doubtfull, where Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity has hitherto been ſilent, &amp; where we have not the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of conſulting it; we enjoy the ſelf-ſame freedom, with all the rights &amp; priviledges of exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing our Reaſon &amp; Judgment.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:43611:47"/>
               <p n="3">3. In leſſer doubts, which we can eaſily determine, we are not uſed to go to any man for counſel: 'tis onely when we are a little puzzled, when we are uneaſy &amp; perplext, 'tis one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then we have recourſe to thoſe who are commiſſion'd to direct us. When we begin to ſpell &amp; pudder upon difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, whether we <hi>may</hi> or <hi>may not,</hi> whether we <hi>ought</hi> or <hi>ought not;</hi> when we plainly find our ſelves at a loſs, &amp; know not how to ſatisfie our mind about the matter before us; when we begin to want a little help, &amp; are glad with all our hearts to call for it: Pray tell me, is there any thing more reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than to refer theſe doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full caſes to the arbitration of a Confeſſor, who is expreſſely deputed by God &amp; his Church,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:43611:48"/>to judge for thoſe who are not capable of judging eaſily &amp; clearly for themſelves? Is not his advice worth our taking, when 'tis worth our asking? When we know not how to chuſe for our ſelves, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prudently reſolve to let our Confeſſor chuſe for us, Why should we quarrel with the ſame Prudence for obliging us to approve his choice? It would be a ſtrange unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perverſeneſs indeed, if when we could not do the work our ſelves, we would not ſuffer any body elſe to do it for us.</p>
               <p>When both parties are wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of an expenſive ſuit of Law, &amp; by common conſent agree to make short work of it, &amp; refer it to the arbitration of a neighbour; If it were your own caſe, &amp; the Sentence were
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:43611:48"/>given againſt you, Would you preſently fly back from your bargain, &amp; refuſe to ſtand to his Judgment? I am ſure no man of Honour would do it. In the ſame manner, when a caſe is doubtfull, when your ſpeculative reaſons are not able to decide it to your ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when you grow quite weary, &amp; deſpair of ending the diſpute; you cannot think of any thing better, than to appeal to the Authority of your Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor; nor can I think of any thing worſe, than to refuſe his Arbitration, when you had not onely accepted, but deſired, it. You know very well, that in any temporal matter, it would not be lookt upon as fair &amp; honeſt dealing. What have you to ſay in your defence?</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:43611:49"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is it fitting that I should ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit without a reaſon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pray, what reaſon had you to conſult him? Was it not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you found your ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied with all your own particular reaſons, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſely abandon'd them to appeal to his Authority? If this were a good reaſon, to <hi>appeal;</hi> why is it not a good one, to <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit?</hi> Is it not a shame, to put ſuch an affront upon the Common Reaſon of mankind, as to uſe it like a bauble, onely fit for childrens-play? and to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways shiſting backwards &amp; forwards, firſt from reaſon to authority, &amp; then from the the ſame authority to the ſame reaſon again? This is never the way to end any diſpute, but always the way to make it endleſs.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:43611:49"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>I do not fly back from Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to my own reaſon, but onely am curious to know his reaſons, becauſe I believe they may be better than mine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet, after all, if he should tell you his reaſons, you would not be ſatisfied with them, till you had well exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined them, &amp; made them your own. His Authority would ſignifie nothing at all; nor his Reaſon neither, any further than your own reaſon approves it. So that, from the Authority which you appeal'd to, you manifeſtly fly back to your own reaſon again. The proudeſt creature in the world, would do as much as this: nor can you shew me the leaſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Chriſtian Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, in this way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:43611:50"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well; but when I am once convinced, I shall be quiet ever after.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ſeems you are vain enough to think ſo, in ſpite of all your dayly experience to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. You know very well, that the <hi>April</hi>-Sun-shine is not more unconſtant, than the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your reaſons. One mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they shine bright, &amp; the next they are under a cloud. How often have you thought your ſelf convinc'd? How oft have you rejoyc'd at it, &amp; thank'd your Confeſſor for it? and preſently after, you have been much more in pain, &amp; more tormented than before. Your ſpeculations, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd to be entirely routed, ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied up again with double for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of recruits, &amp; with a fresh aſſault broke in upon your mind,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:43611:50"/>ruffled your thoughts, and riffled all the treaſure of your peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tis very true; but I beg one anſwer more; onely to this one queſtion: and then I'm confident I shall be ſatisfied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tis a thouſand pities, you should not be ſatisfied, upon ſuch eaſy terms. But pray, conſider how many thouſands of theſe <hi>one-queſtions</hi> you have had an anſwer to already; and all to no other purpoſe, than to render your condition dayly worſe &amp; worſe. Reaſon to Scruples, is like Oyl to Fire: Water may put it out; but Oyl will rather feed it, &amp; encreaſe the Flame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tis Charity in a Confeſſor, to inſtruct me: Is he not my Teacher, as well as my Judge?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: And he is your <hi>Judge</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:43611:51"/>as well as your <hi>Teacher.</hi> His <hi>Charity</hi> does not oblige him, nor his <hi>Prudence</hi> permit him, to <hi>teach</hi> you any thing, but what he <hi>judges</hi> fitting for you. There are a great many truths, which are onely proper to feed your Curioſity, &amp; very unfit to nourish Piety, much leſs, to improve your Humility. When your Confeſſor has judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the caſe, if you ask his reaſons for it, &amp; will not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit till you are thoroughly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied that he is certainly in the right; it is no longer He that judges for you: he onely inſtructs you, &amp; helps you to judge for your ſelf. To what purpoſe are you ſo inquiſitive? Tis a thing not onely need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, but dangerous. For, 1. If it be uſefull to you, he'l inſtruct you, of his own accord: 'tis his
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:43611:51"/>Duty ſo to do: and, if he does not, 'tis his fault, not yours. 2. Although his Conſcience tells him, that it is a great deal better &amp; ſafer for you, not to know his reaſons: yet perhaps his complaiſance, or (if you pleaſe) his good nature, may incline him to hazard the peace of your Soul, by gratifying of your Curioſity: And then you are both to blame; you, for asking; he, for condeſcending.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If Reaſon be a good thing in it ſelf, why may I not ask its And, if my Motive, of deſiring it, be alſo good, why may I not have it for asking?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You have already too much reaſon: you have a great deal more than you well know what to do with: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though it be good in it ſelf 'tis far from being good for you.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:43611:52"/>And truly, if it be not good for you, if you know not what to do with it, if you have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready too much of it, I do not eaſily conceive what ſort of good motive you can have, to wish for more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am very uneaſy with fears &amp; apprehenſions of doing amiſs: this uneaſineſs is a great hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance to me, in my duties &amp; devotions; and therefore I am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways buſy, either ſtudying or enquiring, to find out a clear &amp; certain reaſon, to ſecure me from all fear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I underſtand you very well. You are like a Gentleman who was very uneaſy for fear of wanting money. He thought that if once he could yet the Philoſopher's Stone, it would change all things into Gold, and therefore was always buſy
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:43611:52"/>in ſtudying how to find it out: but 'twas his misfortune, that the thing he ſought for, was not to be found. A <hi>ſpeculative cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty</hi> of the goodneſs &amp; law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs of every particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; every circumſtance of it, would be a fine thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if it were to be had. But before you inquire any further after it, I beg you to conſider how manifeſtly impoſſible it is to diſſect one ſingle action into all its parts, and to read par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular lectures of morality up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, with as many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations to confirm the truth &amp; the exactneſs of them all. 1. In one ſingle action, beſides the ſubſtance of it, our Divines obſerve no leſs than ſix or ſeven general circumſtances, as Perſon, Time, Place, Motive, Means, &amp; Manner of doing.
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:43611:53"/>The harmomy &amp; due propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all theſe muſt firſt be well obſerved &amp; clearly proved, before 'tis poſſible to form a ſpeculative Judgment of the Whole, eſpecially a certain one, which may exclude all fear. 2. Theſe general circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are like ſpawners, and often have a great many little particular ones within them. 3. Even theſe little ones, which hardly are diſcernable by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon eyes, may be diſſected too, &amp; ſtill afford new matter for a Scene of fresh diſcoveries. 4. Some of theſe circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, even thoſe of the greateſt importance, are ſuch thin va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing things, that 'tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for any body's thoughts to lay faſt hold of them. The Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of our Intention, the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of our Endeavours, the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:43611:53"/>Exact proportion of our Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, &amp;c, are things which all the natural Reaſon in the world is never able to demonſtrate. 5. Although the general Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims of Morality are clear &amp; evident, yet nevertheleſs the uſe &amp; application of them of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes are hid &amp; wrapt up in obſcurity &amp; darkneſs. They are like thoſe ſubterraneous ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets which lie too deep for humane induſtry to reach them. The Art of Man can neither fetch them out, &amp; place them in the open light: nor can it contrive a way to go &amp; ſee them where they are; becauſe, in ſuch a deep deſcent, the Lamp burns blew immediatly, &amp; ſoon goes out. Did you ever hear of a man ſo foolish, as to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the digging of a ſtair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe to the Center of the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:43611:54"/>earth? Tis every jot as impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to make a clear diſcovery of Secrets which lie hidden in the center of our Hearts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not this enough to drive a fearfull Soul into Deſpair?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tis very well, if it does ſo. Tis the very thing I would be at. <hi>Deſpair</hi> is not always bad; but ſometimes abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. Many a man has ruin'd a good eſtate, for want of a little deſpair. The Gentleman, I ſpoke of laſt, who was ſo fond of trying coſtly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to find out the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher's Stone, if in good time he had deſpair'd of finding it, he might have ſaved his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, &amp; his eſtate too. The ſooner you deſpair, the better, provided you deſpair in the right place. There are many Souls in Heaven, who would
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:43611:54"/>never have been there, if they had not deſpair'd here. They would never have been ſo much in love with the next world, if they had not deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair'd of being happy in this. They would never have pray'd ſo heartily &amp; ſo devoutly for the aſſiſtance of God's grace, if they had not deſpair'd of being able to work their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation without it. And I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily believe that You your ſelf will never ſubmit ſo humbly, readily, &amp; cheerfully, as you ought, to the Authority of your Confeſſor, till you deſpair enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely of ever finding any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in your own fantaſtical ſpeculations.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:43611:55"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Pretences of Conſcience conſider'd.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TIs impoſſible for a Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Conſcience to be <hi>quiet</hi> without being <hi>certain.</hi> Tis alſo impoſſible, in the darkneſs of moral doubts, to find out any <hi>ſpeculative certainty.</hi> And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently it highly concerns us to conſider what <hi>practical cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty</hi> may be had, and to make the beſt markets we can of it.</p>
               <p>I have, in the beginning of the laſt chapter, already ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd; that in the deciſion of moral doubts our <hi>ſpeculative</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are always ſubordinate to the <hi>practical</hi> principles of our Prudence. Our ſpeculations have no right to any share in the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:43611:55"/>Government of our lives, any further than our Prudential Reaſon, which always ought to have an inſpection over them, approves them as rules to walk by. They have onely a conſulting voice in all deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berations, <hi>when</hi> and <hi>where</hi> they are ſummon'd to appear: Our Soveraign Reaſon ſtill preſides in the Aſſembly: It determines all things, at its own diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not theirs: And, if they happen to grow tedious &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, as oftentimes they are, it has the power to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogue them, or diſſolve them, as it pleaſes; &amp; decide the matter without them.</p>
               <p>So that here are two paths before us, &amp; onely two, which lead us to a <hi>practical certainty:</hi> the one, by way of ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive reaſoning; the other, by
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:43611:56"/>way of Authority: and the main queſtion is; which of theſe two is beſt?</p>
               <p>When we ground our prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical certainty upon the proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of ſpeculative reaſon, we commonly meet with ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty &amp; danger by the way, before we come at it. A long examen oftentimes is neceſſary, to weigh each grain of proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; whether it be more than it need be, or leſs than it should be, or juſt gold-weight. Tis true; a man of ſenſe &amp; ſound judgment, may make a very good shift to overcome the difficulty &amp; the danger too: But how theſe troubleſome cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances will agree with the temper &amp; conſtitution of a ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous Conſcience, I do not ſo eaſily conceive.</p>
               <p>On the other hand, when
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:43611:56"/>all our doubtfull &amp; uncertain ſpeculations are laid aſide, and our practical certainty is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded wholly &amp; entirely upon the Authority of a Confeſſor; the caſe is quite alter'd: 'tis no longer, either difficult or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous. There's no examen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite: no weighing of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity by grains: the leaſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from God, &amp; patent from his Church, is equally eaſy to be known, &amp; equally ſecure to be relied upon. Tis a rule which never varies: 'tis applied the ſame way, to all doubts whatſoever: &amp; the very <hi>A, B, C,</hi> of practical Reaſon, is enough to teach us the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of it. 1. <hi>In all doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full caſes I may ſecurely relie upon my Confeſſor's Authority, without examining his reaſons.</hi> 2. <hi>My preſent difficulty is a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:43611:57"/>caſe:</hi> 3. <hi>And therefore, in my preſent difficulty, I may ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely relie upon his Authority, without examining his reaſons.</hi> This is the whole leſſon: there is no need of any more: and 'tis a leſſon ſo short &amp; ſo plain that a body muſt be very dull indeed, who can be long in learning it. It includes onely three points: 1. the univerſal principle; 2. the application; and 3. the concluſion. The laſt follows evidently from its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: the ſecond cannot fail: the firſt is abſolutely certain: And what can any reaſonable perſon wish for more?</p>
               <p>In the next chapter, I shall make it my buſineſs to prove by Scripture, the abſolute cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of it. Mean time I shall apply my ſelf to conſider the two ſorts of practical cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty:
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:43611:57"/>1. in what they agree; 2. in what they differ; 3. which of the two is better, &amp; more favourably calculated for the eaſe &amp; comfort of a timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Conſcience.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I. <hi>The two ſorts of Practical Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty explain'd.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THey both agree in being equally obſcure, &amp; lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us in the dark, without ſatisfying us <hi>whether or no</hi> the <hi>Action</hi> or <hi>Omiſſion</hi> be lawfull <hi>in it ſelf.</hi> They onely undertake to aſſure us that whether it be lawfull <hi>in it ſelf</hi> or not, 'tis certainly lawfull <hi>to us:</hi> and truly this is as much as a wiſe man would wish for, or a good man needs to care for. Wheth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:43611:58"/>or no it be lawfull <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> is onely a <hi>ſpeculative</hi> doubt; and the deciſion of it, is not neceſſary for our <hi>prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</hi> Tis enough that we have done our duty in enquiring af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it: and that we have either well conſider'd the ſufficient probability of our ſpeculations, or more wiſely conſulted the ſure Authority of our Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor. This done; we are as <hi>ſecure,</hi> as we are <hi>ſincere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Although we are not <hi>ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latively certain</hi> of its being lawfull <hi>in it ſelf;</hi> we are <hi>prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically certain</hi> of its being law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>to us.</hi> We hope the thing is lawfull <hi>in it ſelf.</hi> If we knew for certain that it is not <hi>ſo,</hi> we would not do it. We have done what's fitting for a good Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian to do in doubtfull caſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> More than this we are not obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:43611:58"/>to: And therefore we ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely lay aſide all further care. We are <hi>practically certain</hi> that, if we are miſtaken, we are not guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it. Our God, who ſees our hearts, is as well pleaſed with us, as if we had not been deceiv'd: He will not fail to reward the Sincerity of our good intentions: And when the Humility of blind Obedience goes along with them, they will be acceptable to him upon more accounts than one, and receive a double recompence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II. <hi>When we rely upon our Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor's Authority, our Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty is Abſolute.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ALthough both ſorts of practical certainty agree
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:43611:59"/>in being equally obſcure, on the one ſide; they do not ſo well agree in being equally clear &amp; comfortable, on the other: and the difference is the greater, becauſe it lies in the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of them. The one is grounded upon the Probability of ſpeculative reaſon: the other upon the Authority of a Confeſſor: and betwixt theſe two the difference is greater than many people imagine.</p>
                  <p>When a Penitent judges for himſelf according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of his own ſpeculative reaſon, he muſt take great care to proceed prudently in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations. For,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If he be rash or negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, if he uſe not the caution &amp; circumſpection which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, if he do not well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſufficient probability
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:43611:59"/>of his reaſons, He is ſure to be guilty, whether the thing be lawfull <hi>in it ſelf</hi> or not. For, if it happen to be lawfull, 'tis better fortune than his Rash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs deſerves: And, if it be unlawfull <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſo <hi>to him,</hi> becauſe his Negligence, which he muſt one day anſwer for, can never juſtifie him in it. He may thank himſelf for being miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken: 'tis his own fault, that he is ſo: and 'tis impoſſible for one fault to be a juſt excuſe for another.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If he be partial in exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining the probability of his opinion, if any criminal incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation make him more atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to the one ſide than the other, if he have not patience to conſider the full ſtrength of the reaſons againſt him, but
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:43611:60"/>chiefly apply the whole force of his wit, to magnifie the reaſons which are favourable to his Paſſion, Intereſt, or Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; his Blindneſs is will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: and all the world agrees, that willfull Ignorance is no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe. Tis a common caſe, which dayly happens. We fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently take notice of it, &amp; clearly ſee it, in our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, though we are not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to obſerve it in our ſelves. But the more common it is, the greater is our obligation to conſider the difficulty &amp; the danger to which a Penitent is always expoſed, when he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to judge for himſelf, &amp; to build his <hi>practical certainty</hi> upon the ſandy ground of his own probable reaſons, without removing the rubbish, &amp; exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining well the foundation,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:43611:60"/>before he ventures to raiſe his edifice upon it.</p>
                  <p>He who builds upon a rock, is free from all this trouble. He needs not dig deep to ſearch a foundation, which (without examining) he knows to be as firm as he can wish it. Such is the advantage of that <hi>practical certainty</hi> which is grounded upon the Authority of a Confeſſor. And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this truth, which is of ſuch importance: to all Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, I have amongſt our Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors &amp; Divines made choice of one beyond exception, who not onely teaches it himſelf, but ſays it is the common doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the reſt. He propoſes, &amp; proves, three duties of Blind Obedience, from whence I have drawn three general rules, which are undoubtedly as
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:43611:61"/>lawfull &amp; as commendable in <hi>ſecular</hi> Penitents, as in <hi>religious</hi> Perſons; whoſoever is the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior</hi> of the one, or <hi>Confeſſor</hi> of the other.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. <hi>Although
<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Etiamſi abſolutè falli poſſit Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, id tamen non eſt unquam in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culari praeſumendum, niſi de eo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtet. <hi>Leſſius</hi> de Juſt. &amp; Jure. lib. 2. cap. 46. dub. 5.</note> in general we know</hi> our Confeſſor <hi>may be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken; yet, in particular, we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver are to ſuppoſe He is ſo, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we are CERTAIN of it.</hi> If therefore we are not <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> of his being in the wrong, we may lawfully ſuppoſe, he is in the right: and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,</p>
                  <p n="2">II. We need not
<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Debet eſſe coeca ad ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones praecepti ſcrutandas; nempe ut non velit ſcire cauſas cur quid praecipia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; ſed ſatis ei ſit, praecipi vel imponi ab eo qui locum Dei tenet, nec conſſet per ſe eſſe illicitum. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>ſearch
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:43611:61"/>into his reaſons,</hi> nor <hi>know the cauſes, why he bids us</hi> follow his advice. Becauſe, if we may lawfully ſuppoſe him in the right, 'tis evident we need not be inquiſitive about the matter, for fear of his being in the wrong. And hence it follows alſo, that</p>
                  <p n="3">III. We need not
<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Caeca ad imperfectiones &amp; vitia Superioris, ut haec non conſideret, nec ob haec minus ad obediendum parata ſit; ſed ſolum conſideret eum cujus locum tenet, <hi>ibidem.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his imperfections &amp; his faults; nor be therefore leſs ready to obey him.</hi> Becauſe although his Ignorance or Negligence may poſſibly miſlead him, yet, ſince 'tis none of our buſineſs to enquire about it, we are every jot as ſafe, as if an Angel came from Heaven to aſſure us of his being in the right.</p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:43611:62"/>
                  <p>If you ask me, Why then does <hi>S. F. Sales</hi> adviſe us
<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Introduct.</hi> part. 1. ch. 4. n. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>to chuſe one amongſt ten thous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and?</hi> Why does he tell us, <hi>he muſt be replenish'd with Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Knowledge, &amp; Prudence:</hi> &amp; that <hi>if one of theſe three parts be wanting in him, there is danger?</hi> How shall we <hi>chuſe</hi> a Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, without <hi>conſidering his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections &amp; his faults?</hi> The Anſwer to all this, is eaſily found in the ſame chapter.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When <hi>B. Sales</hi> ſpeaks of <hi>chuſing one in ten thouſand,</hi> he no more intends that we should enter into a ſtrict examen of our Confeſſor's capacity, than he means that we should ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from Confeſſion, till we have ten thouſand Confeſſors at our ſervice. The <hi>number</hi> and the <hi>choice</hi> are neither of them
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:43611:62"/>to be underſtood in the rigour of the expreſſion: becauſe it would then follow, that none but ſome few Soveraign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces could ever be able to go to Confeſſion, for want of <hi>number</hi> enough to <hi>chuſe</hi> in. But nevertheleſs, this way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing is very proper to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceive ſome people, who are not at all ſollicitous what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor they have; provided he be a man for their purpoſe, a man of their own humour, or a man who is eaſily prevail'd with, to let them do as they pleaſe. As for his <hi>Charity,</hi> they do not deſire it; his <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> they do not want it; &amp; his <hi>Prudence</hi> alſo may be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, becauſe they have enough of their own. To oppoſe this pernicious maxim, our Saint aſſures us, <hi>there are fewer to be
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:43611:63"/>found than men imagine, who are fit &amp; capable of ſuch an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; &amp; that there is danger, if</hi> by our fault <hi>theſe parts are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in him;</hi> that is, if we pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely make choice of a man, for this very reaſon, becauſe we believe him deficient in theſe excellent Qualities, &amp; becauſe we are ſo proud &amp; willfull that we cannot endure to deal with a man whoſe <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Prudence</hi> may enable him to <hi>direct</hi> us, or a man whoſe <hi>Charity</hi> may eaſily inſpire him with ſufficient cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, when he is obliged, to <hi>contradict</hi> us. They who know their Paſſions are ſtrong, &amp; think their Reaſon is ſo too, are little deſirous of being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, &amp; leſs of being contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted. And therefore <hi>B. Sales</hi>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:43611:63"/>takes notice that
<note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>ibid.</hi> n. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>one of the laſt advices of the great S.</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wis <hi>to his Son, was in this kind: Confeſs often, &amp; chuſe a Confeſſor of learning &amp; diſcretion, that can &amp; dares advertiſe thee, to do ſuch things as are neceſſary for thy Salvation.</hi> If all the world would follow this advice, there would not be ſo many as there are, who purpoſely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void thoſe Confeſſors <hi>who can &amp; dare advertiſe</hi> them. Their ignorance, when they miſtake, is willfull &amp; cannot excuſe them: but on the contrary, they deſerve to be abandon'd in their darkneſs, becauſe they purpoſely took care to avoid the light.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>B. Sales</hi> ſays not one ſyllable of a Penitent's being obliged to make a ſtrict enquiry
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:43611:64"/>into the Knowledge Charity &amp; Prudence of a Confeſſor. He knew very well that ſuch a method would expoſe them to an infinity of rash judgments, &amp; that God would never give a bleſſing to ſuch a way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding. Tis true; we cannot help ſeeing &amp; hearing: neither can we avoid thinking of what we ſee &amp; hear: and, if the appearances are very great, we may make a reaſonable uſe of them, by way of a prudent caution: we may wiſely &amp; ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chuſe the man who ſeems the better qualified &amp; fitter for the Office: but all this while, we need not form a peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory judgment in the caſe; and after all, we may perhaps be grievouſly miſtaken in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. For which reaſon <hi>B. Sales</hi> is ſo far from adviſing us to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:43611:64"/>conſider well the faults &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections of a Confeſſor, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we chuſe him, that he onely ſends us to our prayers, to
<note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>ib.</hi> n. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>demand him inſtantly at the hands of Almighty God;</hi> and, <hi>having once obtain'd him,</hi> he bids us <hi>bleſs his Divine Majeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for ſo great a benefit.</hi> He tells us, that the way to find a good Confeſſor, is to
<note n="(g)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>ib.</hi> n. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>fear God, &amp; with an humble mind affectuouſly deſire</hi> our <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement in Piety.</hi> He tells us, that we ought to <hi>pray to God with very great inſtance,</hi> to <hi>furnish us with one according to his heart.</hi> He tells us more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, for our comfort, that, <hi>although it were needfull to ſend an Angel from Heaven, as he did to young</hi> Tobias, <hi>he will</hi> not fail to ſupply our want,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:43611:65"/>but that <hi>he will</hi> undoubtedly <hi>give</hi> us <hi>a good &amp; faithfull Guide.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. He expreſſely teaches, that we
<note n="(h)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>ib.</hi> n. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>ought to hearken to</hi> our <hi>Confeſſor, as to an Angel deſcended from Heaven, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct</hi> us <hi>thither:</hi> And any man who has his thoughts about him, muſt needs perceive that, if this be true, the rules of <hi>Leſſius</hi> cannot poſſibly be falſe. For, if we were once aſſured of an <hi>Angel</hi> being ſent from Heaven to direct us,</p>
                  <p n="1">I. We never could ſuppoſe that God, who ſent him, had permitted him to <hi>miſtake</hi> his meſſage, <hi>unleſs we were CER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAIN of it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. The reſpect we owe to an Ambaſſador from Heaven, would not ſuffer us to queſtion
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:43611:65"/>any of his orders, by <hi>ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the reaſons</hi> &amp; endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to <hi>know the cauſes</hi> of them.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. Though <hi>nothing</hi> be <hi>good</hi> &amp; perfect <hi>but God,</hi> yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs it would be a very ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd thing, if we were <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leſs ready to obey him,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, with curious obſervation, we may poſſibly diſcover <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections,</hi> even in an <hi>Angel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My veneration for <hi>S. F. Sales</hi> has led me a great deal further than I firſt intended: but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it has not led me out of my way; becauſe I was going to prove, that the <hi>practical cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty</hi> which is grounded upon the ſure Authority of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, is <hi>abſolute;</hi> without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring any terms on our ſide to ſupport it: whereas the other, which is grounded upon
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:43611:66"/>the Probability of ſpeculative reaſon, is onely <hi>conditional,</hi> and always ſuppoſes ſome certain articles to be obſerved exactly on our part; ſo that <hi>if</hi> we fail in the performance of theſe conditions, all our appearances of practical certainty will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſufficient to excuſe us.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III. <hi>When we depend upon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of our own Reaſon, our Certainty is onely Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the laſt Section I compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that <hi>practical certainty,</hi> which is grounded upon a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor's Authority, to a build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which is raiſed upon a rock: But as for the other, which is grounded upon Probability, I
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:43611:66"/>cannot compare it better than to a building erected upon a floating iſland. Such an edifice, may be made as ſtrong as one pleaſes, &amp; as well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted in it ſelf: but the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is naturally a little ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picious; it may break; it may ſink; and either the one, or the other, is enough to ruine the inhabitants. If the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation never fall to pieces, if it never be ſwallow'd up; All's well. But how shall a body do to be thoroughly ſatisfied concerning theſe matters? Such <hi>if</hi>'s as theſe are a little trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to a man's thoughts; and very well deſerve to be conſider'd, before one ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to dwell in ſuch a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring &amp; uncertain habitation.</p>
                  <p>For the better underſtanding of the whole matter, I shall
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:43611:67"/>endeavour to give a short and familiar account of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon notions of Probability. There are two ſorts of it: the one, intrinſecal; the other, extrinſecal: Intrinſecal Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility is when we conſider the <hi>real merits</hi> of the <hi>cauſe,</hi> the principles &amp; conſequences of it, the arguments &amp; reaſons which have a particular rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to it, or a natural con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion with it. Extrinſecal Probability is when we have no regard to any of theſe things, but onely conſider the <hi>perſonal merits</hi> of the <hi>author</hi> who has credit with us. We have ſome particular reaſons, beſt known to our ſelves, which make us think him wiſe &amp; good, and the greater the appearances are of his being <hi>wiſe</hi> enough to <hi>know</hi> the truth,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:43611:67"/>&amp; <hi>good</hi> enough to <hi>tell</hi> it us ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, the greater is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of his doctrine being true, &amp; the more we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to rely upon it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out enquiring into the reaſons of it. We ſuppoſe his reaſons are <hi>good,</hi> becauſe they are <hi>his,</hi> And becauſe his <hi>perſonal merits</hi> are altogether forreign to the <hi>merits of the cauſe,</hi> therefore this ſort of probability is call'd extrinſecal.</p>
                  <p>When I ſpeak of <hi>authors,</hi> I mean <hi>books</hi> as well as <hi>men,</hi> For we converſe with both, and value them more or leſs, according as we fancy they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it. Some there are, who are much inclined to prefer the <hi>dead</hi> authors before the <hi>living</hi> ones: But I am much afraid, they have no great reaſon for it. A <hi>book,</hi> ſay they, is free
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:43611:68"/>from paſſion intereſt &amp; humour. Very true, it is ſo: and ſo is the <hi>man</hi> himſelf, when he is dead: But he was alive, when he was writing; and, for ought we know, his paſſion intereſt &amp; humour might be then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, as well as he. Be it how it will, I am ſure the <hi>living</hi> authors have ſome very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable advantages over the <hi>dead</hi> ones. 1. The <hi>living</hi> can ſpeak for themſelves; and, if they are not rightly underſtood, they can explain the difficulty more clearly. The <hi>dead</hi> can ſpeak no more; and, if we do not underſtand the text, they are not now in a capacity of putting a comment in the margent. 2. We may acquaint a <hi>living</hi> author with the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular circumſtances of our caſe; but a <hi>dead</hi> one has no
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:43611:68"/>ears to hear us. We may read his writings, and obſerve what general doctrines he lays down before us: But, as there are few rules without ſome excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, we may ſtill be in a doubt; and, if we are, he is not able to reſolve us. So that upon the whole matter, there appears to be as much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as betwixt a Doctor &amp; a Diſpenſatory. And I am very confident, that ſeveral people have loſt their lives by tampe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with Diſpenſatories, who otherwiſe might have enjoy'd both life &amp; health, if they had but, in time, conſulted their Doctor. In fine, whether the <hi>Author</hi> be living or dead, 'tis certain that we either conſider the merit of his reaſons, or the merit of his perſon. If we relie upon the merit of his arguments,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:43611:69"/>having examin'd them, poſſeſs'd them, &amp; made them our own, our probability is what they call <hi>intrinſecal.</hi> But if we wave his reaſons, &amp; rely entirely upon the merit his perſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are perſwaded that a <hi>wiſe</hi> man is not eaſily miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, nor a <hi>good</hi> man eaſily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd upon to tell a lie, our probability is meerly <hi>extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let us now apply theſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to our preſent purpoſe. Tis certainly lawfull to follow a probable opinion: and, wheth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the probability be intrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal or extrinſecal, 'tis no great matter, provided it be ſufficient. We are are onely obliged to look before we leap, and to conſider well the ground before we offer to go upon it. I have already explain'd the difficulty
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:43611:69"/>of examining, &amp; the danger of chuſing our opinion: I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo intimated, that any judicious perſon may eaſily make a very good shift to overcome the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty &amp; the danger too; in confirmation of which, I shall onely add one plain reflection. We are not obliged to uſe any extraordinary care &amp; diligence in conſidering &amp; ſearching the probability of our opinion: 'tis enough that we proceed with the ſame ſeriouſneſs &amp; induſtry of endeavour, which we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly uſe in worldly affairs, ſuch as are of ſome importance to us. For example: If we ſeek truth with the ſame ardour &amp; vigour, as we ſeek a temporal advantage; if we go to look for it, with as good a will as men go uſually to their mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets or their fairs; if we are
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:43611:70"/>in as good earneſt, and as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full about it, as we are in driv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a bargain; if we reject the plauſible ſuggeſtions of our paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, intereſt, or humour, as we do the flattering words &amp; kind inſinuations of a perſon whom we verily believe to have a deſign of over-reaching us: If we do but this (and all this is no more than what we dayly do) We need not fear: We are Secure.</p>
                  <p>Whenſoever a man has done as much as I have here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, the <hi>lawfullneſs</hi> of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his opinion is very <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> although the <hi>truth</hi> of it be onely <hi>probable.</hi> He has a <hi>prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical certainty</hi> that the thing is lawfull <hi>to him,</hi> although he onely has a <hi>ſpeculative probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of its being lawfull <hi>in it ſelf.</hi> And this alone is enough to
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:43611:70"/>pacifie the minds of all conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate perſons: for they will eaſily aſſure themſelves of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving done as much as I have here explain'd; and then, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though their certainty be onely <hi>conditional,</hi> yet being well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of having perform'd the conditions, they are as ſafe &amp; as much at eaſe, as if their certainty were <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But it is not ſo with ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous people who are always more or leſs confounded &amp; amaz'd with too much fear. Nothing but an <hi>abſolute</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty will do their work, a <hi>conditional</hi> one will never ſerve their turn. Neither is it any wonder, that Scrupuloſity and Probability can never agree; becauſe Probability is naturally more or leſs defective, &amp; Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puloſity
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:43611:71"/>is always ſo uneaſy, ſo exceptious, ſo unreaſonable in its expectations, that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to pleaſe it. Tis a pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vish ſort of Humour, which is always finding fault, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſuſpecting the worſt; and when things are as well as they need be, it quarrels with them becauſe they are not better than they can be. In theſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, Probability is blamed, without deſerving it. For, in moral doubts where ſpeculative certainty is not to be found, a reaſonable probability is as much as the matter will bear, 'tis as much as all our ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations can diſcover, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is a very good thing in it ſelf. But, as good as it is, it is not ſo good as Scrupuloſity would have it be. Scrupuloſity would fain be ſpeculatively cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain;
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:43611:71"/>&amp; Probability can never be ſo: and therefore they can never agree upon the point. Now, for my part, I cannot but look upon this, as a very extravagant humour: For, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a man may poſſibly be ſo covetous, as to wish he could make a groat of two-pence; yet however, 'tis evidently an unreaſonable thing, to refuſe a good two-pence, becauſe it is not worth a groat.</p>
                  <p>If ſcrupulous people could poſſibly content themſelves with a reaſonable proportion of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, there might be ſome hopes of their finding comfort in it. But they are ſo exceſſively fond of <hi>certainty,</hi> that they can never reſt without it; and would be almoſt ready to die with deſpair, if they did not live in hopes of it. For this reaſon,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:43611:72"/>they are ſo very buſy in ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the <hi>greateſt</hi> probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as being the neareſt to it: and indeed they are not to be blamed for thinking that the <hi>greateſt</hi> is the <hi>beſt:</hi> but, on the contrary, they very much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be commended for being moſt pleaſed with it, and for making it part of their chief buſineſs to find it. But the truth is, all exceſs is blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, even in things the moſt excellent: and the juſteſt cauſe in the world can never juſtifie the intemperance of any paſſion in the proſecution of it. Their fault lies in their being over-much concern'd, &amp; being blinded with too much fear; which undoubtedly diſpleaſes God, as much as a loving con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence would pleaſe him. They are like a man, whoſe maſter
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:43611:72"/>ſends him to the wood; <hi>Go, fetch me,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the beſt ſtick you can find.</hi> If he had ſaid, <hi>a good one,</hi> the work had been eaſily done: but becauſe he ſaid, <hi>the beſt,</hi> therefore the poor man is ſo terribly afraid, he ſcarce knows where to turn himſelf: firſt, one ſtick pleaſes him: and then another; and another: the more variety he meets with, the more he is confounded with it; and, the more he is ſollicitous to chuſe the <hi>beſt,</hi> the leſs he is able to do it. Thus he wanders up &amp; down, Ioſes his labour, loſes his patience, loſes himſelf; and, by the time that he has found himſelf again, he has loſt his Maſters favour, by ſtaying ſo very long, &amp; chuſing the worſt ſtick at laſt.</p>
                  <p>This immoderate ſollicitude
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:43611:73"/>were yet more pardonable, if when they find the probability they ſeek for, they would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelves to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with it. But the ſame cowardly Spirit which puzzles them in the purſuit of it, does as much diſcourage them even when they think they have found it. When they have overtaken it, &amp; ſee it fall quite short of their beloved certainty, they reckon all their labour loſt, &amp; are as much unſatisfied as ever. They are utterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed in their expectation. They thought to arrive at ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative certainty by the way of probability: But they onely wearied themſelves with trying the experiment, &amp; found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as much miſtaken, as little children are, who looking upwards from the bottom of
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:43611:73"/>a great mountain, are apt to imagine 'tis as high as Heaven; &amp; that, if they were once at the top of it, they could touch the Skie with their hands: Pleas'd with the fancy, they reſolve to try: but the higher they climb, the leſs hopes they have, &amp; when they come there, they find the Skie as much above their heads as ever.</p>
                  <p>Tis in vain to tell ſuch ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous perſons that, although <hi>Innocent</hi> XI. has condemn'd the
<note n="(i)" place="bottom">Generatim dum probabilitate, ſive intrinſecâ, ſive extrinſecâ, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumvis tenui, modò à probabilitatis fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus non exeatur, confiſi aliquid agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ſemper prudenter agimus. <hi>Prop.</hi> 3. <hi>inter</hi> 65.</note> 
                     <hi>leaſt</hi> probability, yet <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> VIII. has approved the
<note n="(k)" place="bottom">Non licet ſequi opinio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, vel inter probabiles probabiliſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam. <hi>Prop.</hi> 3. <hi>inter</hi> 31.</note> 
                     <hi>greateſt.</hi> Nor is it to any
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:43611:74"/>purpoſe to talk to them of a middle way, &amp; to let them know there are degrees of <hi>greater</hi> &amp; <hi>leſſer</hi> betwixt the two extreams of <hi>leaſt</hi> and <hi>greateſt.</hi> If you tell them that, although the <hi>leſſer</hi> be warmly diſputed, yet both parties are agreed that the <hi>greater</hi> is ſufficient. All this will never pacifie their minds: becauſe the <hi>greateſt</hi> probability is always mixt with ſome little degree of uncertainty; and this uncertainty though never ſo little, is a breach which they find wide enough for thouſands of fears to enter, &amp; rush in upon them. Their fears are as unaccountable as thoſe of little children, who are terrified with wonderfull ſtories of Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; Spirits: though you shut the door as cloſe as ever you can, yet if once they get
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:43611:74"/>a fancy in their head, that the bug-bears can creep in at the key-hole, they'l quake and tremble as much, as if the door were wide open.</p>
                  <p>Tis no leſs in vain to aſſure them that, although the caſe in queſtion <hi>may be</hi> ſinfull &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> yet having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſuch pains to find the truth, it is impoſſible that this <hi>may-be</hi> should ever do them the leaſt harm: becauſe, although their probability falls short of ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive certainty, yet shey are <hi>prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically certain</hi> that the caſe is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent &amp; lawfull <hi>to them, if</hi> they have not been <hi>negligent</hi> in exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining it, or <hi>if</hi> they have not been <hi>partial</hi> in approving it. A Security upon doubtfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, is no ſecurity at all; and the conditions here ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, are always doubtfull to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:43611:75"/>them. Alas! They never think themſelves ſufficiently <hi>Sincere</hi> &amp; <hi>Diligent:</hi> and therefore theſe <hi>if</hi>'s can never comfort them, becauſe theſe <hi>if</hi>'s are the very things they are ſo much afraid of. Their firſt apprehenſions are, that the thing perhaps <hi>may be</hi> unlawfull <hi>in it ſelf.</hi> After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, when they begin to aim at a <hi>conditional</hi> certainty, &amp; to conſider well the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>if</hi>'s; their fears are now doubled, inſtead of their being double-guarded from them. They are now allarm'd with fresh recruits of new-rais'd rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which aſſault them in two ſeveral places at once, and with greater numbers than before. And now their thoughts are buſy &amp; uneaſy with endleſs doubts &amp; ſuſpicious, that <hi>may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be</hi> they have been <hi>negligent,</hi> &amp;
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:43611:75"/>
                     <hi>may-be</hi> they have been <hi>partial.</hi> So that all the comfort, which their <hi>conditional</hi> certainty affords them, ſerves onely to furnish them with <hi>two may-be</hi>'s in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>one:</hi> which is juſt a down-right Tinkering of the matter, by mending <hi>one</hi> hole, &amp; making <hi>two</hi> in the place of it. And therefore I need not add a word more, to prove that the <hi>abſolute</hi> practical certainty, which is grounded upon the ſure Authority of a Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, is the better certainty of the two, and much more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably calculated for the eaſe &amp; comfort of a Timorous Conſcience.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:43611:76"/>
                  <head>SECT. IV. <hi>Objections of pretended Conſcience anſwer'd.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TIs high time now to anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer the objections of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Conſcience. I call it it <hi>pretended,</hi> becauſe it goes by a name which it does not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally deſerve, a name is none of its own. Tis a <hi>pretence</hi> which people make uſe of, when they have a mind to <hi>think</hi> what they <hi>will,</hi> and <hi>do</hi> what they <hi>pleaſe.</hi> A <hi>pretence,</hi> by which they cheat themſelves, as well as their neighbours; and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to avoid private remor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as well as publick cenſures, by calling upon the ſacred name of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The main Objection, which
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:43611:76"/>gives ground to all the reſt, is this. <hi>Although the practiſe be lawfull in it ſelf, yet, if I</hi> think really <hi>it is a Sin, my</hi> thinking ſo <hi>is it not enough to</hi> make <hi>it a Sin?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In anſwer to this, I frankly own, that <hi>Conſcience,</hi> rightly underſtood, is the true Judge of our Actions: but ſcrupulous perſons are grievouſly miſtaken in it. All their ſpeculations paſs for <hi>Conſcientious:</hi> all their up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart fancies uſurp the title of <hi>Conſcience:</hi> Humility, Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, &amp; all the train of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues which attend them, muſt now &amp; then be turn'd out of doors, to make room for a Sin-making thought, which they are pleas'd to dignifie with the venerable Character of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> The Government of Reaſon would be a pretty ſort
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:43611:77"/>of a thing indeed, if every thought, which occurs to our mind, were the right rule of our morality. It would be juſt like a non-ſenſical Monarchy, where every body is King <hi>de jure.</hi> Tis true; our Conſcience is always our immediate Judge: but then there is ſcarce one <hi>thought</hi> in a hundred, which is really our <hi>Conſcience:</hi> and, if they are not our Conſcience, 'tis no matter <hi>what</hi> they are, or <hi>how many.</hi> There may ariſe in our minds a thouſand of them (if you pleaſe) one after another; and every one of theſe <hi>thoughts</hi> may <hi>really think</hi> it <hi>is a Sin;</hi> and yet, if <hi>it is not</hi> a Sin <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> theſe <hi>thoughts</hi> will never be able to <hi>make</hi> it <hi>a Sin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Well. But how shall I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern that</hi> thought, <hi>which is my</hi>
                     <pb n="141" facs="tcp:43611:77"/>Conſcience, <hi>from all thoſe which are not?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>How do you know the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt the <hi>Judge</hi> who ſits upon the Bench, &amp; the <hi>Lawyers</hi> who plead at the Bar, We have every one of us a Court of <hi>Judicature</hi> within us, where all our doubtfull caſes are try'd &amp; judg'd. All our <hi>thoughts</hi> which are concern'd in any thing belonging to the <hi>Trial,</hi> are ſummon'd to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in <hi>Court.</hi> Our <hi>ſpeculative Thoughts</hi> are the <hi>Lawyers,</hi> which open the Caſe, explain the circumſtances of it, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the reaſons which are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for it or againſt it. Whilſt the matter is thus under debate our <hi>Thoughts</hi> are divided upon the point: One way, they plead <hi>it is a Sin;</hi> the other way, they plead <hi>it is not.</hi> Mean
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:43611:78"/>time, theſe <hi>thoughts</hi> are meerly <hi>ſpeculative;</hi> becauſe they are not rules to walk by, but are onely the opinion of the <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers,</hi> whoſe buſineſs is to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute</hi> the queſtion, &amp; not to <hi>decide</hi> it. Amongſt all the <hi>Thoughts</hi> which are employ'd in the whole Trial, there is onely <hi>One,</hi> which finally deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines &amp; judges the Caſe. This <hi>Thought</hi> is <hi>practical,</hi> becauſe it is the <hi>Opinion</hi> of the <hi>Judge,</hi> the <hi>Sentence</hi> of the <hi>Court,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Rule</hi> of our <hi>Practiſe.</hi> And <hi>This</hi> is the onely <hi>Thought</hi> which deſerves the name of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I purpoſely make uſe of this Alluſion, to avoid School-terms; becauſe I write for thoſe who commonly are not well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with them. And, for the better underſtanding of the main point, I shall endeavour to give
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:43611:78"/>a familiar account of three general caſes which uſually occur in the aforeſaid Trial.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. It happens ſometimes, that the Lawyers, who plead <hi>it is a Sin,</hi> are able to prove it ſo plauſibly, and with ſuch ſtrong appearance of Reaſon, that the adverſe party is quite confounded and ſilenc'd. And then indeed, the Court being free from noiſe, the <hi>Judge</hi>'s voice may eaſily be heard: and we may be aſſur'd it is our <hi>Conſcience</hi> which tells us, <hi>it is</hi> certainly <hi>a Sin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. Sometimes it happens that the <hi>Lawyers,</hi> who plead it <hi>lawfull,</hi> have the greater probability on their ſide: But yet the others are obſtinate in maintaining the probability of its being <hi>a Sin.</hi> In this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, there is a great noiſe in
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:43611:79"/>Court: The <hi>Judge</hi> pronounces <hi>ſentence,</hi> that the thing <hi>is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full:</hi> The <hi>Lawyers</hi> are imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, &amp; the ſame time cry, <hi>it is a Sin:</hi> And in this confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion we may eaſily miſtake a <hi>Lawyer</hi>'s voice, &amp; think it is the <hi>Judge</hi>'s. Our <hi>Conſcience</hi> thinks it <hi>lawfull:</hi> and at the ſame time theſe unmannerly <hi>Thoughts</hi> continue clamorous, &amp; ſtill <hi>think really</hi> it is <hi>a Sin.</hi> But let them ſtill <hi>think</hi> on; as long, &amp; as <hi>really,</hi> as they pleaſe; 'tis certain they are never able to make it <hi>really</hi> be one.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. At other times it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly happens, that the <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers,</hi> who plead it <hi>lawfull,</hi> although they have great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability on their ſide, yet they do not inſiſt upon it: they wave all probable reaſons, as being
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:43611:79"/>more or leſs defective: &amp; one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ground their defence upon a <hi>practical principle,</hi> which is an undoubted maxim of the Law, that <hi>in all doubtfull caſes one may ſecurely relie upon</hi> a <hi>Confeſſor's Authority, without examining</hi> the <hi>reaſons.</hi> In this caſe, the <hi>Lawyers,</hi> who plead <hi>it is a Sin,</hi> are bafled &amp; quite put out of countenance. As for <hi>ſpeculative certainty,</hi> which now is neceſſary to gain their point, they frankly own they have it not about them; And, as for <hi>probability,</hi> although they have abundance of it, yet the beſt being manifeſtly <hi>uncertain,</hi> the others deſpiſe it, &amp; will not take the pains to anſwer it, but onely oppoſe the <hi>certain rule</hi> of a Confeſſor's <hi>Authority</hi> againſt it. When things are in this poſture, the Trial is ſoon
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:43611:80"/>ended. Our <hi>Conſcience</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly pronounces <hi>Sentence,</hi> that the thing <hi>is certainly lawfull:</hi> and the Equity of this Sentence is ſo viſible, that 'tis impoſſible to be miſtaken in it.</p>
                  <p>According to theſe three caſes, 'tis eaſy to give a short &amp; plain Anſwer to the Queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here propoſed: <hi>If I</hi> think really <hi>it is a Sin, is not my</hi> thinking ſo <hi>enough to make it a Sin?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. In the <hi>firſt</hi> caſe, you <hi>think</hi> 'tis <hi>certainly a Sin;</hi> you do not doubt the leaſt but that it is ſo: And then indeed, although it be not a Sin <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> This <hi>thought,</hi> as long as it continues <hi>thus</hi> certain, <hi>is enough to make it one.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. In the <hi>ſecond</hi> caſe, you have two <hi>thoughts</hi> in your mind at once: one way, you think
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:43611:80"/>it <hi>lawfull;</hi> the other way, you think it <hi>a Sin:</hi> And, if the firſt <hi>Thought</hi> be your <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> the ſecond cannot make it a Sin. But if you are not able to diſcern, which of the two <hi>thoughts</hi> is the dictate of your <hi>Conſcience,</hi> you muſt be content to ſuffer the <hi>mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of being in a <hi>doubt,</hi> whether it be <hi>enough</hi> to make <hi>it a Sin,</hi> or not. But you have ſtill this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort left, that</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In the <hi>third</hi> caſe, when you lay aſide all theſe uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain probabilities, and ground your ſelf entirely upon the ſure Authority of your Confeſſor, This <hi>mortifying doubt</hi> is eaſily and clearly reſolv'd. For, whilſt your <hi>Conſcience</hi> relies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>certainty</hi> of his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity who tells you <hi>it is lawfull,</hi> 'tis manifeſt that all your oth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:43611:81"/>
                     <hi>thoughts</hi> can never be <hi>enough to make it a Sin.</hi> They may be clamorous, they may be troubleſome, they may afright you with more or leſs proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of its being <hi>unlawfull:</hi> But as long as you rely upon a <hi>certain rule,</hi> which always is a juſt excuſe, &amp; always makes your practice <hi>certainly</hi> lawfull <hi>to you;</hi> What ſignifie the vain appearances of <hi>probability,</hi> which always is <hi>uncertain,</hi> and never can amount to more than this, that <hi>perhaps</hi> 'tis really unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>in it ſelf?</hi> Will any body in their right ſenſes, quit a <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> hold, to faſten upon a meer <hi>perhaps?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But may I then ſafely fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low my Confeſſor's Advice, when my own opinion ſeems to me more probable?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Who doubts it? His Advice
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:43611:81"/>is a <hi>certain</hi> rule: your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion contrary to it, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo probable, is ſtill <hi>uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain:</hi> And therefore 'tis an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Truth, that you may
<note n="(l)" place="bottom">Parum refert quod oppoſita ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia ipſi operanti videatur probabilior ſpeculativè: Speculativum enim illud judicium, eo ipſo quod fortè <hi>incertum</hi> &amp; falſum ſit, non debet eſſe regula operationis; cum operans aliam regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam, eamque <hi>certam</hi> habeat, quam ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quatur, <hi>Buſenbaum.</hi> l. 1. tr. 1. c. 2. dub. 2. Quando Religioſus dubitat utrum ſua infirmitas ſufficiat ad non jejunandum, vel ad non legendum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras; non ſolum ad mandatum, ſed etiam <hi>conſilium</hi> ſui Praelati <hi>ſecurè</hi> poteſt abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere a jejunio, vel ab horis. <hi>Sylvius.</hi> in 1.2. q. 19.25. d. 8. c. 1. Praelato praecipienti Religioſus <hi>tenetur</hi> obedire contra ſuam propriam opinionem, etiamſi <hi>probabiliorem.</hi> ibid. d. 9. c. 4.</note> ſafely follow his advice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But what if I am ſtill uneaſy in my ſelf, &amp; terribly afraid it is a Sin? May I ſecurely follow
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:43611:82"/>his Advice; in ſpite of all my fears?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Undoubtedly you may. Is it not evident, that we may always follow a <hi>certain rule,</hi> in ſpite of all the <hi>uncertainties</hi> in the world? And have not we juſt reaſon to
<note n="(m)" place="bottom">Poteſt firmiter operari <hi>contempto</hi> ſcrupulo, etiamſi <hi>perſeveret. Suarez.</hi> in 1.2. diſp. 12. ſect. 4. n. 5.</note> contemn our fears, when we are ſure of being more afraid than hurt?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My fears,</hi> you'l ſay, <hi>are grounded upon a great many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular reaſons: And is it not an unreaſonable thing to turn theſe reaſons out of doors, without firſt confuting them?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Pray, is it not an unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thing to undertake the needleſs labour of an endleſs work? Are they not abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:43611:82"/>
                     <hi>confuted</hi> by their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion? They onely boaſt their <hi>probability;</hi> they do not ſo much as pretend to a <hi>ſpeculative cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty:</hi> And nothing leſs than <hi>that</hi> can ever be allow'd to take place of a <hi>certain</hi> practical direction.</p>
                  <p>The whole truth of the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs is this. Our <hi>ſpeculative thoughts</hi> are proud and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. They would fain uſurp the whole conduct of our life &amp; actions: and This is what they were never made for. They are like a factious Houſe of Commons, who are always quarrelling with the King's Prerogatives, under the odious name of Arbitrary Power: and if care be not taken to keep them within their due limits, they'l ſoon ſubvert the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: they'l convene without
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:43611:83"/>being call'd, and continue ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting even when they are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogued. From whence it plainly follows, that our <hi>Practical Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> is never more Prudent, and more like it ſelf, in the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full exerciſe of its Soveraign Power, than when it ſilences and diſmiſſes theſe pragmatical Scruples &amp; rebellious Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which cannot endure to have <hi>Authority</hi> reign over them. Then it is that our Practical Reaſon is like an Abſolute Monarch, who governs as he pleaſes, without conſulting his Parliament. And here, I hope you will not ſay, that <hi>Reaſon</hi> is <hi>Tyrannical,</hi> unleſs you have a mind to have it ſaid, that <hi>Tyranny</hi> is <hi>reaſonable.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:43611:83"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>The Security of Blind Obedience proved by Scripture.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Pretended Conſcience which claims a <hi>liberty</hi> of <hi>thinking</hi> what it pleaſes, &amp; pleads a <hi>neceſſity</hi> of <hi>doing</hi> what it thinks, is as miſchievous a Tool as the Devil himſelf would wish to go to work with. All the Laws of God &amp; his Church would ſignifie juſt nothing, if every body might pretend to ſay, <hi>My Conſcience tells me another thing,</hi> and <hi>Who shall controll or judge my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?</hi> Tis evident that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the <hi>Law</hi> ſays one thing, &amp; our <hi>pretended Conſcience</hi> takes upon it to ſay another, or whenſoever there ariſes any
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:43611:84"/>diſpute, which of the two is in the right, We do not live in conformity to the <hi>Law,</hi> if we <hi>deſpiſe</hi> ſuch <hi>Judges</hi> of the Law, as the Law it ſelf has appointed.</p>
               <p>My buſineſs therefore at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent is to prove by <hi>Scripture,</hi> that <hi>our Confeſſors are appointed by God, to be the Judges of the Law.</hi> From whence 'twill clearly follow, that <hi>in all doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full caſes we may ſecurely relie upon our Confeſſors Authority, without examining their reaſons.</hi> For ſurely nothing can be more ſelf-evident than this, that <hi>the Law of God can never punish us, for ſubmitting humbly &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely to thoſe Judges, which God himſelf has appointed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are ſeveral Texts of <hi>Scripture</hi> which plainly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto us, how unfitting &amp;
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:43611:84"/>how unſafe a thing it is, to take upon us to be our own judges in all things.
<note n="(n)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Rely not upon your own Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: Be not wiſe in your own eyes.</hi> And again
<note n="(o)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.12.</note>. <hi>There is more hope of a fool, than of one that is wiſe in his own conceit.</hi> Such expreſſions as theſe are very proper to awaken ſome people, who are ſo ſtrangely fond of their own fancies, that they cannot endure to ſubmit them to any Confeſſor what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. They love dearly to <hi>rely upon their own underſtanding</hi> in every thing, although the Word of God expreſſely advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the contrary. They are ſo <hi>Wiſe in their own eyes,</hi> that they never think their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor wiſe enough to direct them. And, let them ſay what
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:43611:85"/>they will, 'tis manifeſt they are not guilty of too much Humility. For, if they thought their <hi>conceits</hi> were <hi>ſilly,</hi> they would eaſily ſubmit. But the true reaſon why they are ſo ſtiff in their opinions, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they always are inclined to believe that their <hi>conceits</hi> are <hi>wiſe</hi> ones. And how does this agree with the Word of God, which in
<note n="(p)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.16.</note> both Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taments admonishes them not to be <hi>wiſe in their own conceits?</hi> But a word is enough to the <hi>wiſe;</hi> and therefore I shall ſay no more upon this ſubject, but shall chieflly inſiſt upon thoſe Texts, which tell us plainly who they are, whom God has appointed to be our Guides &amp; Judges: our Guides, to chuſe our way, &amp; our Judges to determine all our doubts concerning it.</p>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:43611:85"/>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>The
<note n="(q)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Malach.</hi> 2.7.</note> lips of the Prieſt shall keep Knowledge, and they shall ſeek the Law at his mouth: for he is the Angel of the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> And the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon holds good, although his wickedneſs (which God forbid) should
<note n="(r)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>ib.</hi> v. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>make</hi> him <hi>contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible before the people.</hi> His per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal failings do not leſſen the Authority of his Character. He may <hi>know</hi> the Law as well as thoſe who <hi>obſerve</hi> it. And although his actions diſcover the corruption of his <hi>Heart</hi> which contradicts his <hi>Judgment,</hi> yet perhaps he may not labour under any temptation of bely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Law with his <hi>lips,</hi> or contradicting it with his <hi>mouth.</hi> In the old Teſtament we read that
<note n="(s)" place="bottom">1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 8.1, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>when Samuel was old</hi>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:43611:86"/>&amp; <hi>made his Sons Judges over Iſrael, they walk'd not in his ways;</hi> for which reaſon <hi>the Elders of Iſrael,</hi> being offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the wickedneſs of his Sons, <hi>gather'd themſelves toget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her, and came to Samuel, &amp; ſaid, Now make us a King to judge us, like all the Nations.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Samuel,</hi> being <hi>diſpleaſed</hi> with their petition, <hi>prayd</hi> to God to direct him, &amp; God himſelf expreſs'd his diſpleaſure in theſe terms, <hi>They have not rejected thee, but they have rejected me, that I should not reign over them.</hi> And in the New Teſtament we read, that <hi>Jeſus ſaid to the multitude
<note n="(t)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 23.1.2.3.</note> The Scribes &amp; Phariſees have ſitten in Moſes ſeat; All therefore whatſoever they ſay to ye, that obſerve ye, &amp; do ye; but do
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:43611:86"/>not</hi> ſquare your actions <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their works; for they ſay, &amp; do not.</hi> And indeed our Natural Reaſon is enough to teach us the Equity of this Truth. For, when once a Judge is appointed by the Law, although a private perſon at the Bar may juſtly hope him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the better man of the two; yet, if he should there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore offer to juſtle him off the Bench, &amp; diſown the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Comiſſion, ſuch an inſolence would never be endur'd in any Form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>He
<note n="(u)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.16.</note> that hears you,</hi> ſays <hi>Chriſt</hi> to his Diſciples, <hi>hears me: and he that deſpiſes you, deſpiſes me.</hi> This Text shews plainly that
<note n="(w)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1.</note> 
                  <hi>God who ſpoke, in time paſt, to the
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:43611:87"/>Fathers by the Prophets,</hi> and <hi>in theſe laſt days ſpoke unto us by his Son,</hi> now ſtill continues ſpeaking to us by our Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, who though they
<note n="(x)" place="bottom">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>are not ſufficient of themſelves,</hi> yet <hi>God has made</hi> them <hi>able Minis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the New Teſtament;
<note n="(y)" place="bottom">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9.20.</note> and has committed to</hi> them <hi>the word of Reconciliation,</hi> So that we ought to look upon them as <hi>Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, as if God</hi> himſelf <hi>did exhort</hi> us <hi>by</hi> them. If we had been preſent at the Transfiguration of our Saviour, &amp; had heard that
<note n="(z)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.35.</note> 
                  <hi>voice which came out of the cloud, ſaying, This is my beloved Son, Hear him:</hi> What a mighty influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence would it have had upon our Minds &amp; Hearts? And ought not we as much to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:43611:87"/>the voice of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as if we heard a voice from <hi>Heaven?</hi> When our Saviour tells us, <hi>He that hears</hi> my Miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>hears me;</hi> although our fears may raiſe a miſt, &amp; quite ſurround us with a cloud, yet ſtill theſe words of his are like a <hi>Voice out of the cloud,</hi> and a Voice as eaſy to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, as if he had ſaid, <hi>Thoſe are my beloved Miniſters, Hear them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I shall onely take notice of one particular circumſtance, which I hope will help to make ſome people ſenſible of the importance of this Text. I mean thoſe who are ſo ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly terrified with thinking, that their Confeſſions never are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act, that they never love God above all things, that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver do ſufficient pennance for
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:43611:88"/>their Sins, that they are not in the State of Grace, and that they are not in the number of God's Elect. If they are ſo terribly afraid of being
<note n="(a)" place="bottom">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25.</note> 
                  <hi>like Sheep</hi> which are <hi>going aſtray;</hi> if they are ſincerely deſirous <hi>to return unto the Shepherd of their Souls;</hi> Let them harken ſeriouſly to the voice of
<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20.</note> 
                  <hi>that great Shepherd of the Sheep</hi> who ſays,
<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Jo.</hi> 10.14.</note> 
                  <hi>I am the good Paſtor.
<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>ib. v.</hi> 27.</note> My Sheep,</hi> ſays he, <hi>hear my voice, and they follow me.</hi> We cannot <hi>follow Chriſt</hi> unleſs we <hi>hear his voice:</hi> But, if we <hi>hear his voice,</hi> &amp; <hi>follow</hi> it, This is the certain mark, that we are in the number of his Sheep. <hi>My Sheep hear my voice, &amp; they follow me;
<note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>ib. v.</hi> 28.29.</note> and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:43611:88"/>I give unto them Eternal Life; &amp; they shall not perish for ever; neither shall any one pull them out of my Father's hand. My Father, that which he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me, is greater than all: and no one is able to pull them out of my Father's hand.</hi> What a comfort is it, to be thus aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that if we <hi>hear his voice,</hi> and <hi>follow</hi> it, he will not fail to <hi>give</hi> us <hi>Eternal</hi> Life! What a joy, to think that we <hi>shall never perish!</hi> And how does it tranſport &amp; ravish us, when we conſider that although the World, the Flesh, &amp; all the Devils in Hell conſpire againſt us, yet our <hi>Father in Heaven is greater than all;</hi> &amp;, if we <hi>hear the voice</hi> of his <hi>Son, No one</hi> will ever be <hi>able to pull us out of our Father's hand?</hi> What would we give, what would
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:43611:89"/>we do, what would we ſuffer, to be ſure that we are in the happy number of thoſe who <hi>hear the voice</hi> of <hi>Chriſt!</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member therefore, and conſider what he ſays; <hi>If you hear</hi> his Miniſters, <hi>you hear</hi> him; and if you <hi>deſpiſe</hi> them, you <hi>deſpiſe</hi> him.</p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>When</hi> our Saviour <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended
<note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8, 11, 12, 14.</note> he gave Paſtors and Teachers,</hi> not onely <hi>for the work of the Miniſtry,</hi> and <hi>for the edifying the body Chriſt,</hi> but alſo <hi>that we henceforth be no more children, toſs'd to &amp; fro, &amp; carried about with every wind of doctrine.</hi> And certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, unleſs they were appointed by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be our Guides &amp; Judges, tis very hard to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, how they should hinder us from being <hi>toſs'd to &amp; fro,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:43611:89"/>&amp; carried about with</hi> what <hi>wind of doctrine</hi> we pleaſe. But the thing which here is moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, is this: Before he <hi>went
<note n="(g)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Jo.</hi> 16.5, 7.</note> his way to him that ſent</hi> him, He ſaid, <hi>I tell you the truth, It is expedient for you that I go away.</hi> Which words being extended to the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Faithfull, to whom the <hi>Comforter</hi> was <hi>ſent</hi> as well as to the Diſciples, 'tis hard to forbear the ſtarting of a very material queſtion: How? Is it <hi>expedient for us</hi> to exchange an <hi>infallible</hi> Guide, for a company of Confeſſors, who are every one of them <hi>fallible?</hi> Yes. It certainly is ſo. For, 1. Our Submiſſion is <hi>equally ſecure,</hi> and that's as good: 2. Our Obedience is <hi>more humble,</hi> and that's a great deal better.</p>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:43611:90"/>
               <p>If you ask me, By what Authority we can be <hi>ſo ſecure</hi> under the direction of a fallible Guide? Pray, is not <hi>his</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſufficient who will, one day, <hi>come to judge the quick &amp; the dead?</hi> Can you imagine, he is ſo unjuſt, as to condemn us for ſubmitting humbly &amp; ſincerely to <hi>his</hi> own <hi>Authority?</hi> And, if he cannot poſſibly condemn us for it, are we not <hi>ſecure?</hi> Tis he himſelf (who knows a great deal better than we do, how fallible they are) 'tis He, I ſay, who has appointed them to be our Judges; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis by his appointment, that in doubtfull matters we ſubmit our judgment to them. Hear what he ſays himſelf:
<note n="(h)" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Jo.</hi> 20.21, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>As my Father hath ſent me even ſo I ſend</hi> them. <hi>Whoſe ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:43611:90"/>they Sins</hi> they <hi>remit, they are remitted unto them; and whoſe ſoever ſins</hi> they <hi>retain, they are retained.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I shall add no gloſs to this Text. The <hi>Church of God</hi> is the beſt interpreter of his <hi>Word.</hi> She is
<note n="(i)" place="bottom">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15.</note> 
                  <hi>the pillar &amp; the ground of Truth.</hi> If we believe our <hi>Creed;</hi> if we believe the <hi>Holy Catholick Church;</hi> If we believe the ſolemn declaration of a <hi>General Council</hi> approved &amp; univerſally receiv'd, There is nothing more certain than that our <hi>Confeſſors</hi> are by <hi>Chriſt</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <hi>Judges</hi> to diſcern &amp; to determine all matters belonging to Confeſſion. The words of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> are theſe.
<note n="(k)" place="bottom">Dominus noſter Jeſus Chriſtus, à terris aſcenſurus ad coelos, Sacerdotes ſui ipſius Vicarios reliquit, tanquam praeſides &amp; judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ad quos omnia mortalia crimina deferantur; quo, pro poteſtate Clavium remiſſionis aut retentionis peccatorum, ſententiam pronuncient, <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 14. cap. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Our Lord JESUS
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:43611:91"/>CHRIST before he aſcended from Earth to Heaven, left Prieſts his Vicegerents, as Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents &amp; Judges, to whom all mortall Sins are to be declared, that they may accordingly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Sentence.</hi> So plain it is, that our Ghoſtly Fathers have their <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> &amp; <hi>Patent</hi> from his <hi>Church,</hi> to be our <hi>Judges</hi> in matters of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> and conſequently to <hi>pronounce</hi> a final <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence</hi> upon all our <hi>doubtfull caſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:43611:91"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Maxims of</hi> S. Bernard, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Blind Obedience.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Have now done with <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> and, to give an account of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> I have made choice of <hi>S. Bernard,</hi> whom I look upon as the laſt Father of the Church, &amp; the beſt able to expreſs the ſentiments of all the reſt who went before him. His eminent Learning &amp; Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue were the Oracle as well as Miracle of the twelfth Age. His Doctrine &amp; Example were the greaſt Inſtruction &amp; the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of all: when in the darkneſs &amp; the coldneſs of thoſe times, which were the winter-ſeaſon of Devotion, he unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectedly appeard, like <hi>fire</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:43611:92"/>
                  <hi>ſent</hi> from Heaven to enlighten &amp; enflame the minds &amp; hearts of ignorant &amp; tepid Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>He has written a whole book particularly upon this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject: and, the whole care of his life being chiefly employ'd in cultivating &amp; improving the <hi>Vertue</hi> of <hi>Blind Obedience,</hi> we may very well allow him to have rightly underſtood it. He diſcourſes, for the moſt part, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the blind obedience which is due to a <hi>Prelate</hi> or <hi>Superior,</hi> addreſſing himſelf par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to <hi>Religious</hi> perſons, who by vow are bound to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it. But nevertheleſs the Submiſſion, which is due from all Penitents to their Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, is a Caſe exactly parallel to it, &amp; is directly compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended under the general no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:43611:92"/>of it. And beſides, 'tis obvious to every body's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe, that thoſe practiſes which are univerſally reputed vertuous in a Cloiſter, can never be juſtly cenſur'd as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull in the World: but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Religious <hi>muſt</hi> do, the Seculars <hi>may</hi> lawfully do it, if they pleaſe.</p>
               <div n="1" type="maxim">
                  <head>MAX. I. <hi>We ought to look upon our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor as a Vicegerent of God, without conſidering his faults.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <p>
                           <hi>WHether
<note n="(l)" place="bottom">Sive Deus, ſive homo Vicarius Dei, mandatum quodcunque tradiderit; pari profecto obſequendum eſt curâ, pari reverentiâ deferendum. <hi>S. Bern.</hi> lib. de praecept. &amp; diſpen. cap. 9.</note> it be God, or Man his Vicegerent, who impoſes an obligation upon
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:43611:93"/>us, we are to obey with the ſame care, and ſubmit with the ſame reſpect.
<note n="(m)" place="bottom">Quid enim intereſt, utrum per ſe an per ſuos miniſtros, ſive homines ſive Angelos, hominibus innoteſcat ſuum placitum Deus? Quamobrem quicquid vice Dei praecipit homo, quod non ſit <hi>certum</hi> diſplicere Deo; haud ſecus omnino accipiendum quam ſi praecipiat Deus. Praeſertim cum teneas de Scripturis, quia Labia Sacerdotis cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodiunt ſcientiam, &amp; legem de ore ejus requirunt; quia Angelus Domini exercituum eſt. Requirunt, dixerim, Legem; non quam ratio manifeſta pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baverit, ſed quod ita latere aut obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſſe cognoſcitur, ut in <hi>dubium</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire poſſit, utrumne Deus ſic an aliter fortè velit, ſi non de labiis cuſtodienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſcientiam, &amp; ex ore Angeli Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni exercituum <hi>certum</hi> reddatur, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                              </note> What matter is it, whether God impart his will &amp; pleaſure to us, by himſelf, or by the Miniſtry of Men, or Angels? Whatſoever it is that Man pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes, as Vicegerent of God, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:43611:93"/>it be CERTAINLY diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to him, we ought to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it in the ſame manner, as if God himſelf had ordain'd it. Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſince we read in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that the lips of the Prieſt keep knowledge, &amp; they require the Law at his mouth, becauſe he is the Angel of the Lord of Hoſts. They ſeek the Law,</hi> ſays he, <hi>not in things which our Reaſon proves MANIFESTLY to us, but in matters which are ſo hidden &amp; obſcure, that we might poſſibly DOUBT, wheth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er God would have it ſo, or not; unleſs it were MADE CER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAIN, by thoſe lips which are the Keepers of Knowledge, &amp; by the mouth of the Angel of the Lord of Hoſts.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>Can any man ſpeak more plainly than <hi>S. Bernard</hi> does, upon this occaſion?</p>
                  <pb n="174" facs="tcp:43611:94"/>
                  <p>And now, perhaps, ſome body may be apt to ſay; If I had but ſuch a man as <hi>S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> for my Confeſſor, I could rely upon his word as confidently as if God himſelf had ſaid it: but when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the weakneſs &amp; the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion of my Ghoſtly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I dare not venture to truſt him.</p>
                  <p>To this Objection a learned Divine returns this Anſwer, that Penitents do not rely upon their Confeſſor
<note n="(n)" place="bottom">Dicet fortaſſe quiſpiam, ſi talis mihi eſſet Praelatus, qualis erat <hi>S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardus,</hi> facilè acquieſcerem: nunc verò dum Superioris mei parvam ſapientiam aſpicio, non audeo ei acquieſcere. R. Inferiores non obediunt Praelato, quia ſit <hi>doctus,</hi> quia <hi>prudens,</hi> quia <hi>Sanctus,</hi> ſed quia vicem Dei gerit, hoc ipſo quo eſt legitimus ſuperior <hi>Sylvius.</hi> in 1.2. q. 19. a. 5. d. 12. c. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>becauſe he is
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:43611:94"/>LEARNED, PRUDENT, or VERTUOUS, but barely becauſe he ſupplies the place of God,</hi> who has appointed him to be their Judge in all doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full matters relating to Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. But ſince you own ſo frankly, that if you had <hi>S. Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> for your Confeſſor, you could eaſily rely upon him: Hear what <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſays himſelf.
<note n="(o)" place="bottom">Non te moveat Magiſter impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus, indiſcreta poteſtas; ſed memento quia non eſt poteſtas niſi à Deo, &amp; qui reſiſtit poteſtati, reſiſtit Dei ordinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. <hi>S. Bern.</hi> Serm. 41. de diverſis.</note> 
                     <hi>Be not afrighted at the unskillfullneſs of his Teash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or the indiſcretion of his Authority; but remember that there is no power but of God; and that they who reſiſt Authority, reſiſt the ordinance of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Tis true, This Maxim of
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:43611:95"/>
                     <hi>S. Bernard</hi> allows of one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception from the general rule, which is, that when we are <hi>abſolutely certain</hi> of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor's being miſtaken, we may lawfully refuſe to ſubmit to him.
<note n="(p)" place="bottom">De hujuſmodi nec praeceptor expectandus, nec prohibitor auſcultan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus eſt. <hi>S. Bern.</hi> lib. de praecep. &amp; diſpen. cap. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>In theſe things,</hi> ſays he, <hi>we neither expect any body's Teaching, nor mind any body's Forbidding.</hi> But here it is that all Timorous Conſciences muſt have a great care, of not <hi>being miſtaken</hi> themſelves, when they think their Confeſſor <hi>is ſo.</hi> The <hi>Exception</hi> is very true, but they muſt be carefull not to deſtroy the <hi>Rule</hi> with it. They are apt to fear on the wrong ſide; and Fear is a ſtrange Paſſion, which commonly miſrepreſents
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:43611:95"/>whatever comes in its way. They look at every thing with a pair of ſpectacles made of falſe glaſſes, the one magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the Sin, the other multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the circumſtances, &amp; both conſpiring to deceive them. In this condition they conſult their Confeſſor, and tell him a terrible Story, which, by their good will, they would never make an end of. Their Confeſſor, who is generally well acquainted with theſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, &amp; ſoon ſees what they would be at, begins to cut them short: And 'tis no wonder he does ſo, becauſe he ſees things plainly, with his own natural eyes, &amp; will not be prevail'd upon to uſe their ſpectacles, becauſe he knows what glaſs they are made of. Now, this offends them ſtrangely; and
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:43611:96"/>without any more adoe, they think they have all the reaſon in the world to conclude. He's <hi>certainly</hi> miſtaken. He allows them, may be, onely half a quarter to examine; and they are <hi>certain</hi> that three or four hours are too little, for the purpoſe. They are <hi>certain</hi> they ought to confeſs ſome things, which he forbids them to ſpeak of. They are <hi>certain</hi> they are obliged in Conſcience, to make a general Confeſſion; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he tells them, they need it no more than they do the head-ake.</p>
                  <p>Poor Creatures! In theſe perplexities they <hi>mean</hi> very well; but they <hi>do</hi> very ill. For, even in things which ſeem evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to them, they ought to beware of being miſtaken, &amp; of making things matter of
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:43611:96"/>Conſcience which are far from being ſo. They ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware the ſetting up of a falſe God to themſelves, &amp; ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing all the Duties of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to an Idol of their own invention. Their pretended Conſcience is neither better nor truer for the heat &amp; zeal with which they maintain it. Even Heathens themſelves are oftentimes more zealous than Chriſtians: And (the Devil helping his ſervants) it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly obſerved, that men are fiercer in the wrong than in the right. Who would ſet up a fallible Guide againſt an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible one? This Conſcience of theirs is fallible, not onely <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> but alſo <hi>to them,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when, by their fault, it is erroneous, is does not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them. But their Confeſſor
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:43611:97"/>is always infallible <hi>to them,</hi> although he never is ſo <hi>in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;</hi> becauſe it is infallibly true, that they are always excuſed, when in any doubt they hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly &amp; ſincerely follow his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
                  <p>When nothing elſe will do, They chiefly inſiſt upon this; that they are very <hi>certain</hi> their Confeſſor does not rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them, becauſe they are ſure that, if he did, he would certainly be of their opinion. But ſurely ſuch a pleaſant argument as this, is little better than that of Poet <hi>Bayes. When I have a mind,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to know whether a man be a man of parts, or not; What do me I, but give him one of my Plays to read? He reads it. If he likes it; Well. If not; I know what to think of him.</hi>
                     <pb n="181" facs="tcp:43611:97"/>Much at this rate, theſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple go to their Confeſſor, with one of their huge &amp; mighty Scruples. He hears it. If he approves their opinion; All's well. If not; They know for <hi>certain</hi> he muſt needs be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſſly miſtaken.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tis very hard,</hi> you'l ſay, <hi>for people to think otherwiſe: Eſpecially when they can</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>ſwear, they are in the right.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The prouder they are, the harder it is: but if they were ſufficiently humble, it would be a very eaſy matter. Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, when they cannot quite <hi>ſwear.</hi> For if their heart goes <hi>pit a pat</hi> with fear of being perjur'd, when they think of laying hand upon the Book &amp; making a ſolemn Oath; Then they may very well aſſure
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:43611:98"/>themſelves, that there is ſtill ſome little doubt lies lurking in their Minds, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they may boldly reckon it amongſt the doubtfull caſes, in which their Confeſſor has full Commiſſion to direct them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>S. Tereſa</hi> was certainly ſo fully perſwaded of her Viſions being true &amp; real, that she could <hi>almoſt</hi> have ſworn, they were ſo: And yet she would not therefore venture to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey her Confeſſor. Hear how <hi>F. Craſſet</hi> deſcribes her beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in this caſe.
<note n="(q)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Conſid. ſurles F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſtes.</hi> Octob. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS appear'd to</hi> S. Tereſa <hi>two ſeveral ways; in his own perſon, &amp; in the perſon of her Confeſſor.</hi> Jeſus <hi>himſelf teaches her infallible truths: Her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, who repreſents him, tells
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:43611:98"/>her, they are ſo many lies. What shall</hi> Tereſa <hi>do? Whom shall she believe? She never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberates upon the matter: She chuſes rather to obey</hi> Jeſus <hi>in the perſon of her Confeſſor, than in his own perſon. I may be miſtaken,</hi> ſays she, <hi>in believing theſe Viſions; but I shall never be miſtaken in obeying my Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectour. I am not abſolutely cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that it is the Son of God who appears to me; but I am certain that it is he who ſpeaks to me by my Superiours. If they tell me otherwiſe than he does, I'l believe them ſooner than him, becauſe he commands me ſo to do.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="maxim">
                  <pb n="184" facs="tcp:43611:99"/>
                  <head>MAX. II. <hi>We ought to look upon him as our Judge, without exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining his reaſons.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <hi>TIs
<note n="(r)" place="bottom">Imperfecti cordis eſt, &amp; infirmae prorſus voluntatis, haerere ad ſingula quae injunguntur; exigere de quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que rationem; &amp; malè ſuſpicari de omni praecepto cujus cauſa latuerit; nec unquam libenter obedire, niſi cum audire contigerit quod fortè li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buerit, aut quod non aliter licere ſeu expedire monſtraverit vel aperta ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, vel indubitata authoritas. Non planè haec eſt illa quae ex Regulâ tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur, <hi>Obedientia ſine mora. S. Bern.</hi> lib. de praecep. &amp; diſpen. c. 10.</note> a Sign of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Heart, and of a very weak Will, to demurr upon every thing that is enjoin'd; to exact a reaſon for every thing; to think ill of every precept which
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:43611:99"/>we do not know the cauſe of; and never to obey willingly, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we bear what pleaſes us, or unleſs the neceſſity or conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of it, be proved by mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt reaſon or by ſome unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Authority. This is far from the Obedience which the Rule requires: OBEDIENCE WITHOUT DELAY.
<note n="(s)" place="bottom">Subditi &amp; obedientes eſſe debem us ad nutum Praepoſitorum, nihil inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogantes propter conſcientiam. <hi>S. Bern.</hi> Serm. 41. de diverſis.</note> We ought to be Submiſſive &amp; Obedient, without aſking any queſtion for Conſcience ſake.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>Theſe words of <hi>S. Bernard</hi> are too plain to need any Comment, and therefore I shall onely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to shew the evils which infallibly attend thoſe people, who will never ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to their Confeſſor in any
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:43611:100"/>particular difficulty, unleſs he firſt give a ſatisfactory reaſon for it, and convince them by meer dint of argument.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To avoid the fear of an imaginary Sin on the one ſide, they put themſelves evidently into a real danger of Sinning on the other.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They affront <hi>Chriſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by rebelling againſt his Government.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They willfully oppoſe the kind deſigns of God's great Mercy to them, in allowing them a Guide.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. To avoid an imaginary Sin, they put themſelves evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently in a real danger of Sinning. <hi>My Confeſſor,</hi> you'l ſay, <hi>is fallible: How dare I rely upon him?</hi> Pray, are not you fallible too? How dare you rely upon your ſelf? If he miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:43611:100"/>'tis his fault: but if you miſtake, 'tis yours. If you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon him without exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining his reaſons, the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is onely his; But if you are inquiſitive &amp; will depend upon your ſelf, you bring the danger to your own door; and, if there be any miſtake, you are juſtly accountable for it. You may e'en thank your ſelf; You ſought for danger, &amp; you found it; You <hi>loved</hi> it, &amp; who can help your <hi>perishing</hi> in it?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But am not I to take care, that my Confeſſor be not miſtaken?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Are not you ashamed to ask ſuch a queſtion? <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Church</hi> have <hi>both</hi> appointed him to be <hi>your Guide:</hi> And muſt you therefore take upon you to be <hi>his?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But whilſt my Confeſſor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:43611:101"/>me, it were to be wisht that ſome body would direct him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That's God's <hi>care.</hi> He him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>takes</hi> that upon him, &amp; excuſes you from troubling your head about it. If you cannot help ſuſpecting that your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor is a bad man, and that therefore God will not direct him: You may make amends for it, by <hi>taking</hi> what <hi>care</hi> you can, to be as good, as you should be, your ſelf: And then (if you humbly deſire it, &amp; hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily pray for it) God will be ſure to direct him for <hi>your</hi> ſake, although he would not do ſo much for <hi>his. B. Sales</hi> adviſes you
<note n="(t)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Introd.</hi> p. 1. ch. 4. n. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>to pray to God with very great inſtance,</hi> and afterwards
<note n="(u)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>ibid.</hi> n. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>not to regard him ſimply as a man, nor to truſt in him, nor in his human prudence, but in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:43611:101"/>of Almighty God, who will undoubtedly favour your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, and ſpeak to you by the interpoſition of this man; putting into his mind, &amp; into his mouth, thoſe things which shall be moſt expedient for your ſpiritual ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement.</hi> In short, there is nothing more certain, than that God will either <hi>direct</hi> him or <hi>excuſe</hi> you. Be it which way it will, your Soul can never be in danger, upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. For, as long as you <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſwear,</hi> your Confeſſor is miſtaken; ſo long you <hi>may</hi> lawfully <hi>ſwear,</hi> you are Secure. <hi>S. Bernard</hi> propoſes the ſame Objection:
<note n="(w)" place="bottom">Sed homines, inquies, facilè falli in Dei voluntate de rebus dubiis percipiendâ, &amp; in praecipiendâ fallere poſſunt. Sed enim, Quid hoc refert tuâ, cui conſcius non es? <hi>S. Bern.</hi> lib. de praecep. &amp; diſpen. c. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>When matters
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:43611:102"/>are doubtfull, Men may eaſily deceive themſelves in diſcerning the will of God, &amp; deceive others in preſcribing it.</hi> To which he roundly anſwers, <hi>What's that to you, as long as you are not certain of it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. They affront <hi>Chriſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by rebelling againſt his Government. He gives their Confeſſor a full Commiſſion, to be their <hi>Judge</hi> in all doubtfull caſes. They will not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him, under that character. They'l hearken to him, as to a <hi>Lawyer</hi> at the <hi>Bar,</hi> if he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: But, as for the <hi>Bench,</hi> they queſtion very much whether he be either <hi>good</hi> enough, or <hi>wiſe</hi> enough, to deſerve that place, ſo well as they do. They'l hear his reaſons, &amp; conſider them: but, when all is done, they are free-born Subjects of
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:43611:102"/>the Almighty, and are <hi>always</hi> reſolv'd to <hi>judge</hi> for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſpeaking of this
<note n="(x)" place="bottom">Elatio contemnentis, atque im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poenitentis obſtinatio, in minimis quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que mandatis culpam facit non mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam, &amp; convertit in crimen gravis rebellionis culpam ſatis levem ſimplicis tranſgreſſionis. <hi>S. Bern.</hi> ibid. c. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>proud Contempt, &amp; Obſtinate continuance in it,</hi> ſays that <hi>even in little precepts it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to more than a little fault, and changes a ſmall trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion into a grievous Crime of Rebellion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. They willfully oppoſe the kind deſigns of God's great Mercy to them, in allowing them a Guide. By giving us a Guide, he puts into our hands the beſt means of ſaving our Souls; he ſupplies us with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual opportunities of practiſing the beſt of moral vertues, <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility</hi>
                     <pb n="192" facs="tcp:43611:103"/>&amp; <hi>Obedience;</hi> he leads us into the beſt &amp; readieſt way of following <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Captain of our Salvation,</hi> who <hi>humbled himſelf</hi> &amp; <hi>became obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient;</hi> for which reaſon <hi>God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted him,</hi> &amp; will exalt us too, provided we follow his example.</p>
                  <p>Theſe were the vertues He required from our firſt Parents: and to make the practiſe more eaſy, He was pleaſed to be their Guide himſelf. He was every way Infallible: his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Wiſdom on the one ſide, &amp; his no leſs infinite Goodneſs on the other, were Vouchers for his Infallibility: And yet their <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Diſobedience</hi> found a way to rob them of their Innocence.</p>
                  <p>To repair this fault of theirs the <hi>Eternal Truth</hi> becomes In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:43611:103"/>the <hi>Word is made Flesh,</hi> and <hi>dwells amongſt us:</hi> He comes to <hi>enlighten all the World,</hi> and to take care that thoſe, who <hi>follow</hi> him, may never <hi>walk in darkneſs.</hi> And here indeed the terms of our <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Humility</hi> ſeem ſomething harder than before; becauſe we cannot now be ſaved, without ſubmiſſion of our Underſtanding &amp; our Will to <hi>Man</hi> as well as <hi>God.</hi> Tis true; This <hi>Man</hi> is <hi>God,</hi> He is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely <hi>Wiſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Good,</hi> He is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every way <hi>Infallible.</hi> But all theſe great &amp; glorious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages are Objects far too bright for our weak eyes, we cannot ſee theſe dazling &amp; amazing truths, but are forced to <hi>believe</hi> without <hi>ſeeing.</hi> Here it is, we <hi>humble</hi> our proud thoughts, &amp; captivate them to
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:43611:104"/>the <hi>obedience</hi> of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> And 'tis the firſt <hi>Croſs</hi> we <hi>take up,</hi> when we begin to <hi>follow</hi> him.</p>
                  <p>But yet this is not all: Neither is it juſt that this should be enough. If we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be <hi>exalted,</hi> we muſt <hi>humble</hi> our ſelves, &amp; be <hi>obedient</hi> one ſtep further. Our Parents would not <hi>ſubmit</hi> to <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and we, who have the ſame blood in our veins, muſt now <hi>ſubmit</hi> not onely to <hi>Man</hi> who is <hi>God,</hi> but to Men who are no more Gods than we are; to <hi>Men</hi> who are as falli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as our ſelves. This is the <hi>Croſs</hi> which we muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity <hi>take up,</hi> if we intend to <hi>follow</hi> him. We muſt be thus far <hi>humble</hi> &amp; <hi>obedient,</hi> if we deſign to be <hi>exalted</hi> with him. To <hi>follow</hi> him, we muſt
<note n="(y)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Jo.</hi> 10.27.</note>
                     <pb n="195" facs="tcp:43611:104"/>
                     <hi>hear his voice:</hi> And, being gone himſelf ſo far before us, What could he contrive better for us, than to leave his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters behind him, and to give us all the encouragement that can be, to rely upon their word; by aſſuring us, that <hi>if we hear</hi> them, <hi>we hear</hi> him? Tis evidently juſt that this ſame proud &amp; ſtubborn Nature of ours, which once aſpired ſo high as to defy <hi>the Higheſt,</hi> should now bow down its head, not onely lower than its Maker, but even lower than the duſt of which he made it. Tis juſt, I ſay, in things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, to reſign our Wills, and in doubtfull matters, to ſubmit our Underſtandings, even to our fallible fellow-creatures who are made of the ſame duſt with us.</p>
                  <pb n="196" facs="tcp:43611:105"/>
                  <p>Tis hard indeed, at firſt, for ſo much Pride and Stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornneſs to yield without ſome little reſiſtance. But however, we are in the hands of a God &amp; a Judge from whom we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make our eſcape, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have reaſon to be glad to kiſs the Rod, although we are not fond of it. Nay, we have reaſon to be fond of it, if we rightly conſider our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. Our Saviour himſelf was pleaſed to tell us, before he <hi>went,</hi> it was <hi>expedient for us</hi> he should <hi>go away.</hi> For although there may be more Difficulty in ſubmitting to his Miniſters, yet the Benefit of it is incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably greater. The ſelf-denyals of our Underſtanding &amp; our Will are more acceptable to God, when they are offer'd to him in the perſon of a Miniſter
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:43611:105"/>who repreſents him. They are more humble, &amp; therefore more acceptable. And here I know not which to admire moſt; the Equity of his Juſtice, in making this the punishment of our Sin; or the Kindneſs of his Mercy, in making it the beſt, the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieſt, &amp; the moſt effectual means of purchaſing our Everlaſting Happineſs: Our <hi>Croſs</hi> indeed, is heavier; but the Reward is greater. The occaſions of <hi>taking</hi> it <hi>up,</hi> are more frequent; but they onely ſerve to multiply the glories of our <hi>Crown,</hi> when we shall, one day, be <hi>exalted</hi> for it.</p>
                  <p>This is <hi>One</hi> kind deſign, which God has laid in order to our future Happineſs: And <hi>this</hi> we willfully oppoſe as often as we refuſe to ſubmit, without a particular &amp; a convincing
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:43611:106"/>reaſon for it. There is certainly no <hi>Humility</hi> in never ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but when our natural Reaſon is convinc'd; nor is there any <hi>Obedience</hi> in never complying, but when we na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally have a mind to it. The very worſt of Atheiſts &amp; Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertins are every jot as <hi>humble</hi> and <hi>obedient</hi> as this: They ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make any difficulty, of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving</hi> what they <hi>ſee,</hi> or <hi>Doing</hi> what they <hi>pleaſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A <hi>Second</hi> deſign of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence in allowing us a Guide, is to make us truly Happy, not onely <hi>hereafter,</hi> but even <hi>here.</hi> Now this is a double Kindneſs, &amp; the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt that can be imagin'd; that God is not contented to crown our Happineſs at our journey's end, but deſires to give us a taſt of it before hand, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:43611:106"/>us as much of it as we are able to carry with us thither. By leading us into the way of <hi>Blind Obedience,</hi> He removes the cauſes of our inward trouble and diſquiet, &amp; lays a ſure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of interiour comfort &amp; tranquillity of mind. And this I shall endeavour to give a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular account of, out of pity &amp; compaſſion to thoſe Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Conſciences, who make it their great deſign to pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but know not how to go about it.</p>
                  <p>One would admire to ſee the ſtrange perverſeneſs and frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardneſs of people, when they are poſſeſs'd with panick fear. Every thing lies croſs in their way. The very shadow of an obligation is enough to put them in a fright<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> What ever it is, they think it morally impoſſible to
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:43611:107"/>be comply'd with; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hate the very thought of it. God gives them a <hi>Guide:</hi> and becauſe this looks as if they were obliged in Conſcience to follow his direction, therefore they ſtart back, &amp; cry, <hi>What is our Reaſon good for, if in doubts we muſt ſubmit it to our Guide?</hi> And yet, if God had bid them rely entirely upon their <hi>Reaſon,</hi> they would perhaps have thought it the harder mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the two, and would have argued the contrary way, <hi>What is our Guide good for, if we may not ſafely relie upon him?</hi> They would fain be doing their duty; and for fear of doing it the wrong way, they never do it right. They are too wiſe to truſt their Confeſſor; and yet they are not wiſe enough to truſt themſelves. They are deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:43611:107"/>fond of <hi>ſpeculative cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty:</hi> but the miſchief is, it is not to be found. <hi>Probability</hi> ſometimes flatters them with hopes of <hi>abſolute certainty;</hi> but always deceives them, &amp; puts them off with doubtfull <hi>if's</hi> &amp; <hi>and's,</hi> which are never able to give them any ſatisfaction. This is the reaſon why they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways fearfull, &amp; always inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive to find out reaſons to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe their fears. But after all their vain endeavours to confirm &amp; ſettle their opinion, they can never attain to a ſteddy &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shaken perſwaſion of it. Their Conſcience ever &amp; anon recoyls upon them; and all their plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible reaſoning is ſtill born down &amp; confuted by a ſtrong ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion which they can never get out of their minds, that perhaps they are ſtill miſtaken.</p>
                  <pb n="202" facs="tcp:43611:108"/>
                  <p>But that which I moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, is the ſtrange obſtinacy of their humour, who after long experience having felt the ſmart of their miſerable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are ſtill reſolved to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in it. They dayly find themſelves at a loſs: They have all the reaſon in the world to conclude they are in the wrong way: And yet they ſtill go on. A Traveller is wiſer than ſo. As ſoon as he finds himſelf out of the way, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſtops his courſe, he turns towards the right way with all the ſpeed he can, and has not the leaſt inclination to go wrong any further. But the minds of theſe people are ſo hurried away, by their unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable prejudices, that though they find themſelves in the wrong, they cannot endure to
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:43611:108"/>return to the right. They ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to ſee an end of all their fears, &amp; then they intend to be as obedient as you pleaſe. Mean time, they beg pardon, if they defer their Obedience till the practiſe of it be a little more eaſy to them. Now this is a fancy which is every jot as extravagant as that of the <hi>Ideot,</hi> who being come to the river ſide, &amp; being obliged to paſs over, durſt not venture in a boat, but reſolv'd to expect till the water was all gone, &amp; left the channel dry. He ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd the ſwiftneſs of the ſtream, and fancied it would ſoon run quite away, &amp; leave him a free &amp; eaſie paſſage. But the river runs, &amp; ſtill runs on, and though he should ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a thouſand years, 'twould never leave off running. And
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:43611:109"/>ſo 'tis in our preſent caſe. Their doubts &amp; jealouſies, their reaſonings &amp; diſputings, will ſtill run on, &amp; never have an end. Tis impoſſible they should ever have any tolerable enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of themſelves, or ever be able to shake off theſe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting fears, but by ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the <hi>eaſy yoke</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp; by ſecuring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under his protection, whom hitherto they have af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted, by deſpiſing of his Miniſters. Nothing but <hi>Blind Obedience</hi> can free them from all this miſery, by removing the cauſes of their inward trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; diſquiet, &amp; by laying a ſure foundation of interiour comfort &amp; tranquillity of mind.</p>
                  <p>The principal cauſe of their inward trouble, is this. They rely entirely upon their own
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:43611:109"/>judgment: and therefore have juſt reaſon to conclude, that they are unavoidably accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for every miſtake they commit. And this is abundantly enough to make them always jealous, that, for ought they know, God's Juſtice may be making towards them, and his Anger levell'd againſt them. But this cauſe ceaſes immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, as ſoon as they entertain the principles of <hi>Blind Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience:</hi> Becauſe 'tis evident, when God has given them a Confeſſor to direct them, it cannot be his will &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that this Guide should be directed &amp; guided by them. Tis true; He may be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: But let him look to that. Tis none of their buſineſs to examine him: On the contrary 'tis commendable in them to
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:43611:110"/>ſubmit
<note n="(z)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>S. Bernard.</hi> ſup.</note> 
                     <hi>without asking any queſtion for Conſcience ſake.</hi> And therefore, although his miſtakes may perhaps be fatal to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, tis as clear as the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian Sun, that they can never be fatal to them, nor can they ever be accountable for any thing which he adviſes.</p>
                  <p>Another more ſecret cauſe of their inward diſquiet, is well expreſs'd by S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> who ſays, <hi>Thou haſt made us, O Lord, for thy ſelf; &amp; our hearts are always reſtleſs, till we reſt in Thee.</hi> All creatures are uneaſy when they are out of their natural Element. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is at reſt, but whilſt it is in that ſtate which Nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for it. Obedience is the natural ſtate of the Soul: it was made to obey its Maker:
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:43611:110"/>and the conſtant practice of this Vertue, is the condition to which God deſign'd it. He gave us our Reaſon; not to make us Rebels, but to make us reaſonable Subjects: and therefore all our acts of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Authority of his Government, are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional &amp; ſuitable to the firſt inſtitution of our Nature. Our Reaſon is a Ray of the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity; it imprints the image of our Maker on our Souls; and writes the fundamental laws of our Submiſſion, in ſo plain a character, that though our Paſſions now and then obſcure it, yet they never can efface it. As long as
<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note> 
                     <hi>our Souls are ſubject to the higher powers ordain'd by God;
<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                           <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.17.</note>
                        <pb n="208" facs="tcp:43611:111"/>obeying them that rule over us, &amp; ſubmitting our ſelves</hi> to thoſe who <hi>watch for our Souls;</hi> ſo long our Souls are in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural temper, and are in very good health, becauſe they are in that State in which they ought to be, according to the primitive intention of their Being. But when we <hi>reſiſt the power</hi> of Authority; when we
<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2.</note> 
                     <hi>reſiſt the ordinance of God;</hi> when we revolt againſt the Government of <hi>Jeſus-Chriſt,</hi> by deſpiſing the Commiſſion he has given to our Confeſſor, and by refuſing in doubtfull caſes to acknowledge the ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency and ſafety of his Direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; then it is that we act contrary to the inward light of our minds, our Conſcience checks us, and makes us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſy.
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:43611:111"/>And how can we hope to be at eaſe, as long as we have poyſon within us, which puts us in a ſickly &amp; diſeaſed condition? Our Pride and Will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs put all our ſpirits in a continual fermentation. Our minds can never be ſerene, as long as they are clouded with the fumes of our diſtemper. All the common arts of diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion will never avail us: we may change our place, our poſture, our phyſick, &amp; our Phyſician too; but we shall ſtill be reſtleſs, till the cauſe be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, which creates our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbance.
<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Iſai.</hi> 57.21.</note> 
                     <hi>There is no peace, ſays my God, to the wicked.</hi> But, as in our body we find an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible eaſe &amp; pleaſure, when it is in perfect ſtate of health; So when Obedience
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:43611:112"/>corrects the proud and willfull humours of our Soul, reſtores the even temper of our Mind, &amp; ſmooths the way before us; Then it is that All is eaſy to us. We eaſily <hi>know</hi> what we are bid to do: And, being hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, we as eaſily <hi>do</hi> it.</p>
                  <p>The Obedience, which I ſpeak of, not onely removes the cauſes of our inward trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; diſquiet; but lays a ſure foundation of interiour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort &amp; tranquillity of mind, by affording us the beſt <hi>Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> that we can wish for, during Life; and the greateſt <hi>Joy,</hi> that we can think of, at the hour of Death. What grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Security</hi> can our hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, than to be under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of God himſelf, the <hi>Shepherd of our Souls,</hi> who knows a great deal better,
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:43611:112"/>than we do, what is good for us, and will not ſuffer us to <hi>go aſtray,</hi> becauſe he loves us bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than we love our ſelves? He was our Enemy before; whilſt we rebell'd againſt his Government: But, by deteſting our paſt pride &amp; folly, &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to his Miniſters, he now becomes our Friend. All Friendship is comfortable: but this is the beſt of Friendships, and therefore is the greateſt &amp; divineſt comfort. Tis a great ſatisfaction, to feel that we our ſelves love God: and a double ſatisfaction, to hope that He himſelf loves us. Then it is, that we may ſay to our Soul, as <hi>David</hi> did,
<note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 114.7.</note> 
                     <hi>Return unto thy reſt, O my Soul;
<note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.1.</note> My God is my Light, &amp; my Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; Whom shall I fear? My
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:43611:113"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="211" facs="tcp:43611:113"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="212" facs="tcp:43611:114"/>God is the Protector of my Life; of whom shall I be afraid?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As 'tis our beſt <hi>Security;</hi> during life; ſo 'tis our greateſt <hi>Joy</hi> at the approach of Death, and yields moſt comfort then when we ſtand moſt in need of it. Tis a terrible thing to a departing Soul, when it looks back upon a proud &amp; willfull courſe of life, which inſtead of being ſpent in the ſervice of God, has been perpetually em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in idle reaſoning &amp; diſputing, <hi>how</hi> to ſerve him, <hi>when</hi> to ſerve him, &amp; <hi>whether</hi> to ſerve him <hi>or no.</hi> What can ſuch people plead in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half? Tis certainly no good excuſe, to ſay, <hi>Lord, we have always been rebellious againſt thy Government; but the reaſon was, becauſe we were afraid to rely upon it; and indeed, we durſt
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:43611:114"/>not take thy word for it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we thought it fitter for us, in all our doubts, to govern our ſelves according to our own fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Tis true, we have ſeldome, or never, done our Duty; but we hope thou wilt pleaſe to pardon our willfull omiſſions of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we were always ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty buſy in thinking &amp; conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it, that we could never find time to do it.</hi> Here it is, their guilty Conſcience lies in wait to accuſe them, &amp; never is more fierce than in the day of adverſity. When Eternity, that terrifying object, at the hour of death, preſents it ſelf before their thoughts; when they feel themſelves beginning to ſink into the regions of darkneſs; when they are ready to die at the amazing appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of their final Sentence;
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:43611:115"/>How will the Guilt of all their Diſobedience then ſtare them in the face! With what regret &amp; terrour will they then behold it, in its own true shape! What tumults and convulſions will it raiſe within their breaſts, when they obſerve a long black train of proud &amp; willfull practices, which very well deſerve to be attended with a longer &amp; a blacker train of everlaſting mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries!</p>
                  <p>But it is not ſo with thoſe who have in time repented of of their folly, and have proved ſincerely <hi>humble</hi> &amp; <hi>obedient.</hi> In their greateſt temptations, all is calm &amp; ſerene within, when there is nothing but darkneſs &amp; clouds about them. All their their acts of Submiſſion are ſo many ſeeds of peace &amp; comfort ſown in their Conſciences<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb n="215" facs="tcp:43611:115"/>which never fail to ſpring up, &amp; flourish moſt, when the day of diſtreſs approaches. When the pangs of Death are ready to lay hold of them, and they are juſt going to ſtep into the other world, What a ſeaſonable refreshment is it to their thoughts, too look back upon an <hi>humble</hi> &amp; <hi>obedient</hi> courſe of life? Then it is that the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of it over-flows their minds, the joys of Heaven begin to ſpring up in their hearts, &amp; are a true &amp; ſolid comfort which will ſtick cloſe to them &amp; ſtand faithfully by them in the day of Trial, when they have moſt need of it. O what a Joy it is, to conſider that their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>Friend,</hi> who has been hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Shepherd of their Souls,</hi> is now the <hi>Judge</hi> of their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions! to reflect that their <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility</hi>
                     <pb n="216" facs="tcp:43611:116"/>in <hi>hearing</hi> his <hi>Voice,</hi> &amp; their <hi>Obedience</hi> in <hi>following</hi> it, are the certain marks by which he <hi>knows</hi> the happy number of <hi>his Sheep!</hi> and to remember that he will not fail to <hi>ſet them on his right hand,</hi> when He <hi>comes in glory</hi> to pronounce the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of their Everlaſting Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs! To <hi>hear his Voice</hi> was once the <hi>Security</hi> of their life: And to <hi>hear</hi> the <hi>ſame,</hi> is now the <hi>Joy</hi> of their death. <hi>My Sheep,</hi> ſays he, <hi>hear my Voice, &amp; they follow me: and I give unto them Eternal Life: and they shall not perish for ever. Come ye Bleſſed of my Father;</hi> Come &amp; <hi>inherit the Kingdom, which was prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for you, from the foundation of the World.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43611:116"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
